<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lavvfulnes of hearing the publick ministers of the Church of England proved, by Mr. Philip Nye and Mr. John Robinson, two eminent Congregational divines.  Together with the judgment of Dr. Goodwin, Dr. Owen, and other independents, as well ancient as modern, concerning forms of prayer, parish-churches, and communion with them: and the judgment of other nonconformists about kneeling at the sacrament.</title>
            <author>Nye, Philip, 1596?-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203023</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299204</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299204</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179944</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04528)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179944)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2808:49)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lavvfulnes of hearing the publick ministers of the Church of England proved, by Mr. Philip Nye and Mr. John Robinson, two eminent Congregational divines.  Together with the judgment of Dr. Goodwin, Dr. Owen, and other independents, as well ancient as modern, concerning forms of prayer, parish-churches, and communion with them: and the judgment of other nonconformists about kneeling at the sacrament.</title>
                  <author>Nye, Philip, 1596?-1672.</author>
                  <author>Robinson, John, 1575?-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179944:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179944:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LAVVFULNES OF Hearing the Publick Miniſters OF THE <hi>Church of England.</hi> PROVED, By Mr. <hi>PHILIP NYE,</hi> AND Mr. <hi>JOHN ROBINSON,</hi> Two Eminent Congregational Divines.</p>
            <p>Together with the Judgment of Dr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> and other INDEPENDENTS, as well Ancient as Modern, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Forms of Prayer, Pariſh-Churches,</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> with them: And the Judgment of other Nonconformiſts about <hi>Kneeling at the Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed, as well to ſatisfy thoſe that yet ſcruple Communion with the Church, as to vindicate thoſe that have complied, from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Cenſures of thoſe that vilify them, as Temporizers; or that they have done ſo to qualify themſelves for an Office, to ſerve a Turn, or to ſave themſelves from the Penal Laws.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden Lion, in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:179944:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179944:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe deſign of theſe Sheets, is, to ſatisfy the Conſciences of thoſe Diſſenters that hold Communion with the Church of <hi>England</hi> unlawful; beſeeching them ſeriouſly to conſider what is here ſaid (in order to the Church's Peace, and to prevent their deſigned ruin) by Learned and Holy Men that are of the Separation, commonly called <hi>Independents.</hi> I have quoted none of the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Perſwaſion (only in the buſineſs of <hi>kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Sacrament</hi>) becauſe it would be an endleſs work, they generally (both Ancient and Modern) having aſſerted the lawfulneſs of (at leaſt) Lay-Communion with the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And beſides, I perceive their Arguments will not prevail with <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents</hi> who deny a National Church: I know there are many that are convinced it is lawful to Hear Sermons, but not the Liturgy as an impoſed Form. They may find here, what the Reverend and Learned Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> ſays concerning Forms of Prayer, in the latter end of theſe Sheets. And whereas they complain the Church-Prayers are empty Forms; I wiſh they would come and fill them with Spirit and Zeal. But the greateſt Scruple that hinders them, is <hi>kneeling at the Sacrament;</hi> and that which pinches them moſt, is, that this Geſture is ſaid to be <hi>Adoration</hi> given to the Elements; but they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what the Church ſays concerning that Geſture, which me thinks ſhould remove that Scruple, and ſatisfy every reaſonable Man in that particular, which for their ſatisfaction I here quote at large, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas it is ordained in this Office, for the Adminiſtration of the Lord's Supper, that the Communicants ſhould receive the ſame Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<pb facs="tcp:179944:3"/>(which Order is well meant, for a ſignification of our humble and grateful acknowledgment of the Benefits of Chriſt therein given to all worthy Receivers, and for the avoiding of ſuch prophanation, and diſorder in the Holy Communion, as might otherwiſe enſue); Yet, leſt the ſame Kneeling ſhould by any Perſons, either out of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and infirmity, or out of malice and obſtinacy, be miſconſtrued and depraved; It is here declared, that thereby no adoration is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, or ought to be done, either unto the Sacramental Bread and Wine there bodily received, or unto any Corporal Preſence of Chriſt's natural Fleſh and Blood. For the Sacramental Bread and Wine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſtill in their very natural ſubſtances, and therefore may not be adored, (for that were Idolatry to be abhorred of all faithful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians) and the natural Body and Blood of our Saviour Chriſt are in Heaven, and not here; it being againſt the truth of Chriſt's natural Body, to be at one time in more places than one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Caution (which wholly denies Tranſubſtantiation) together with that Prayer about the Gunpowder-Treaſon, being now incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in our Liturgie, do (as Dr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> told a Reverend Doctor of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> now living) make it impoſſible there ſhould be any Reconciliation with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reverend and Learned Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> (an old <hi>Puritan</hi>) ſays to this effect, That that <hi>Adoration</hi> uſed in the Sacrament, is not terminated in the Elements, but a token of Godly Reverence to Chriſt himſelf ſitting in Glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> ſays alſo, That a Man muſt not refuſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament kneeling, when he cannot have it otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Fenner</hi> ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And the Learned Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> ſays, That Geſtures at Receiving, are Moveables, and not of the Free-hold of this Ordinance.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, whether Men are ſatisfied in whole or in part, I wiſh they would conſider ſeriouſly what that excellent Man, Mr. <hi>Jer. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> (a Congregational Divine) ſays, in his <hi>Irenicon,</hi> pag. <hi>182. viz.</hi> That one great dividing Practice hath been this, That <hi>becauſe Men cannot join in all things with others, they will join in nothing.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="religious_treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179944:3"/>
            <head>Mr. PHILIP NY's Reſolution of this Caſe of Conſcience, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Whether we may lawfully hear the Now Conforming Miniſters, who are Re-ordained, and have renounced the Covenant, and ſome of them ſuppoſed to be ſcandalous in their Lives?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwer.</label> FOr the Reſolution of this Caſe, there is a three-fold Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration pertinent.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Conſideration I.</head>
               <head type="sub">About the Duty it ſelf, <hi>Hearing the Word.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>There are four ways by which at this Day the Great God conveyeth the knowledg of himſelf and his Mind unto ſinful Man. 1. His Works of Creation and Providence, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 19.2. 2. The ſuggeſt of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, even the remainder of God's Image in us. 3. The Word or Law of God written, expounded, or applyed in ordinary Preaching. 4. The Church, which is the <hi>Ground and Pillar of Truth,</hi> the Knowledg of God and his Mind is more eſpecially there held forth, by the Gifts given, and Offices therein appointed by Chriſt. Theſe are diſtinct Ways and Methods of God, by which he is pleaſed to make known himſelf: and we are obliged, even by the Law of Nature, to attend when God doth ſpeak; it is therefore an undoubted moral Duty, to attend the ſpeaking of God, in whatſoever way by Providence brought unto us.</p>
               <p>The Scripture, with the Interpretation and Application thereof, commonly termed <hi>Propheſying</hi> or <hi>Preaching,</hi> is one of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Means by which God makes known himſelf to us; this is a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> Gift according as God in his Providence ſhall diſpoſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20.</p>
               <p>Such <hi>National</hi> or Publick Preachers, may be ſaid to have their Call from Chriſt, he having a hand in ordering the Motions of Providence
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179944:4"/>for the Good of his Church, <hi>John</hi> 5.17. And particularly in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential ſending of Miniſters, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.38. and this is the <hi>calling</hi> and <hi>ſending</hi> mentioned, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. The Lord in theſe Adminiſtrations, by Preachers thus ſent, <hi>according to the good Pleaſure of his Will, finds out a People before they ſeek him.</hi> This is a diſpenſation of God to Men as his Creatures.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For Application to the Caſe.</head>
                  <p>The Word of God interpreted and apply'd by preaching in this providential way, is a choice Mercy and Gift, wherewith God hath bleſſed this Nation for many Years, to the Converſion and Edification of many thouſands. The Governors thereof have ſucceſſively, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Light, made divers good Laws and Statutes for improving this Mercy for the beſt advantage of the Nation, as appears in that,
<list>
                        <item>1. There are Schools and Univerſities maintained for the bringing up of Perſons in Learning; alſo there is a conſtant ſetled Maintenance for encouraging of ſuch as ſhall be ſent out to the ſeveral parts of the Nation in this great Work.</item>
                        <item>2. There is a ſum of Doctrinal Truths, which in the Enlargement and Application, are ſufficient both for Converſion and Edification, to which the Preachers are to aſſent; and there is proviſion made by our Laws, that ſuch Perſons only who are <hi>ſound in the Faith</hi> be imployed therein.</item>
                        <item>3. The Inhabitants of this Nation, are required to be preſent, and to give attendance to Inſtruction, that they may <hi>Learn the Fear of the Lord.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Aſſertion.</label> Theſe things being ſo, although ſome of us do enjoy the Inſtruction of our Paſtors being in a Church-Relation, yet it is a Duty that we and our Families frequent alſo (as we have Liberty and Opportunity) the more <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>National</hi> Miniſtry, for theſe Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Reaſon 1.</label> Where the Lord hath appointed various Ways and Methods, in which he will draw near to us, and manifeſt himſelf, we ought to make uſe of all in their place and ſeaſon. This is a ſeveral and diſtinct way or appointment of God, not only in reſpect of <hi>God's Works</hi> and our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> but alſo in reſpect of the <hi>teachings of Church Officers;</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in theſe Particulars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The one is <hi>Cultus Naturalis,</hi> from the firſt Commandment, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the <hi>Light of Nature;</hi> and the other is <hi>Cultus Inſtitutus,</hi> and a Duty of the ſecond Commandment; and our direction herein is only from <hi>Goſpel Light.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179944:4"/>
                     <item> 2. In reſpect of the Perſons that are the <hi>primary Object</hi> of each <hi>Propheſying,</hi> that is, <hi>Church-Preaching,</hi> ſerveth not for them that believe not, but for them which believe. It is principally for building: for a Church-State ſuppoſeth them Believers, though ſuch preaching hath occaſionally its efficacy in converting the Weak, and more directly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Children of Members. This <hi>National</hi> or <hi>Providential Preaching,</hi> is principally for Converſion, and hath for its primary and main Object, Perſons in their natural Condition; ſuch a Preacher was <hi>Noah,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.3. Preaching is before Believing, and Believing before any Church-Ordinance: There were Preachers in all Nations, and in every City, before there were Churches in every City.</item>
                     <item>3. The one is from <hi>Gifts</hi> only as neceſſarily requiſite, but <hi>Church-Inſtruction</hi> ſuppoſeth the Perſon to be not only of ſome eminency in <hi>Gifts,</hi> but <hi>Grace</hi> alſo, and ſet apart to Office according to Chriſt's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And now having ſeen the difference of theſe two Methods, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence will follow; they ought to be attended with due reverence each of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Reaſon 2.</label> As we are Members of <hi>Churches,</hi> ſo we are Subjects and Members of this <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> and are obliged thereby to obſerve the lawful Command of our Governors, and to be Examples therein to others. As Members alſo of this <hi>Civil</hi> Body, we ought to join with it in a thankful acknowledging this happy Providence of God, by which we, and our Children after us, may be inſtructed; which may be a means to have it continued, and a neglect thereof would give juſt cauſe to fear the contrary.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Reaſon 3.</label> If <hi>Church-Members,</hi> or any <hi>one Godly Man</hi> hath a Warrant to forbear hearing ſuch Miniſters upon this account of unlawfulneſs; then all Godly Men ought at all times ſo to do; and if ſo, the Examples of the Godly to the generality being very leading in the Matters of God, this Ordinance thereby will be little frequented, and of leſs efficacy to thoſe that do come to it. And by aſſerting it unlawful to hear ſuch Miniſters, we imply, it were better for the Nation there were no preaching but in particular Churches: and if ſo, what can we expect will become of many thouſands in an ordinary way of Salvation, that have no benefit at all by our Church-Inſtructions? We are to walk wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yea, mercifully towards them that are without.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:179944:5"/>
                  <head>Objections Anſwered.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 1.</label> Where there is no true Church, there can be no true Miniſtry: the Church of <hi>England</hi> is no true Church, <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> There may be a <hi>Lawful</hi> and <hi>True</hi> Miniſtry, or Adminiſtration of the ſaving Truths of God, though the Nation, or any parcels of it as yet be in no <hi>Church-State.</hi> We ſay, each <hi>particular Church</hi> materially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, is <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>Church Catholick.</hi> The <hi>Matter</hi> muſt needs have being before the <hi>Form</hi> can be introduced. No Man becomes a Member of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> but by his effectual Calling, and that is by preaching the Word. I conclude therefore each <hi>particular Church</hi> to have its production from ſuch an Adminiſtration, and not this Miniſtry to have its original or ſtate from the Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 2.</label> The National Miniſtry is Antichriſtian, derived from <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> If <hi>Antichriſtian:</hi> it's either ſo from their <hi>Standing,</hi> as deriving their Ordination thence, (of which in the <hi>third Conſideration</hi>) or from their <hi>Doctrine.</hi> If any ſuch Doctrine be preached, it's the miſcarriage of particular Perſons, and contrary to the National Proviſion. The <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Religion,</hi> to which the Miniſters are to conform their Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are Orthodox, &amp; framed for the caſting and keeping out of Popery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 3.</label> It offends our weak Brethren; it is a complying with the Corruption of the Times, it's an approbation and encouragement to Conformity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> Theſe, and other Objections of the like nature, have their weight and place in practice when the matter is <hi>indifferent,</hi> and may be done or left undone without Sin, and not in relation to any <hi>moral</hi> Duty. Though I know <hi>gathering</hi> of Churches in a <hi>Congregational</hi> way, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without Ordination, Baptizing of Infants, and the like, as well as hearing a Conforming-Miniſter, are a great offence to ſome that are truly Godly: yet may I not ſay, <hi>If ſuch a Fellowſhip, if ſuch Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and the reſt, offend my Brother, I will do no ſuch thing while the World ſtandeth, leſt I ſhould offend.</hi> It were ſin ſo to reſolve: becauſe theſe are <hi>moral</hi> Duties, and not left to my liberty, as Meats and the reſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13. and <hi>Acts</hi> 8. wherein the nature of indifferent things is laid down.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:179944:5"/>
               <head>Conſideration II.</head>
               <head type="sub">About <hi>refraining</hi> a <hi>Moral</hi> Duty for the Evil mixed with it, or in the Perſons performing it.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. As <hi>we are not to do Evil that Good may come of it,</hi> no more ought we to leave what is <hi>morally</hi> Good undone, for the Evil that is ſome-way mixed with it. Zeal for Good is to be preferred to that which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Evil. The greateſt Good is better than the greateſt Evil is back What-ever good thing we do, tends towards our Union with the chiefeſt Good, the refraining of Evil not ſo immediately.</item>
                  <item>2. Betwixt things <hi>indifferent,</hi> and what is <hi>morally</hi> good, you have this difference. If there be any mixture of evil with the one, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes wholly evil, there is nothing of good in it to give ſtop or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponderate; but what is morally good will remain ſo ſtill, though mixed with evil. We may allay the worth of it, as baſer Metals mixed with Gold, but yet it is Gold ſtill, and may be perfectly ſevered.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>When I would do good,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>evil is preſent with me.</hi> I cannot hear, or read, or pray, and the reſt, but with a mixture of Sin, yet upon this account I may not ceaſe from, or neglect a known Duty, not though <hi>materially</hi> conſidered the evil accompanying being greater than the good; As in meditation, when blaſphemous thoughts ariſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To omit a known Duty is a ſin of wilfulneſs, the evil from me in it is but infirmity only. The leaſt <hi>wilful</hi> Sin is greater and more provoking than the greateſt Sin of <hi>Infirmity.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For Application to the Caſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Governors otherwiſe pious and zealous, yet not ſo knowing in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Church-Orders, may poſſibly in the diſcharging of their Duty, and doing this good Work, occaſion a mixture of evil with it; Being perſwaded that <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>Preaching,</hi> will be accepted with more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and become more effectual, if by Perſons <hi>ordained</hi> as well as <hi>examined</hi> and <hi>tried,</hi> for their fitneſs; and if accompanied alſo with <hi>ſet</hi> and <hi>ſolemn Forms of Prayer,</hi> and other <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformities,</hi> they therefore by their Laws eſtabliſh and enjoyn theſe things. The Perſons alſo appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to this Work (though not approving all that is impoſed) through infirmity yield and ſubmit, rather than let ſo good a Work fall.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The things therefore objected as Evils, by which ſome are deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from hearing, are the <hi>Infirmities</hi> of others mixed with the Duty; I ſay <hi>Infirmities,</hi> for ſo in charity we ought to judg. Now if I may not omit a Duty in reſpect to the Evil mixed with it, which is my own, much leſs may I thus leave an Ordinance for the Evil that is another Man's, no way mine, or to be charged upon me. This were to make another Man's Sins or Infirmities more mine than my own.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:179944:6"/>
                  <head>Objections Anſwered.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 1.</label> We cannot judg ſuch Impoſition, and ſubmitting to theſe Infirmities, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after ſo much Light and Reformation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 1.</label> If the known <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> of ſome of them who have <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> is ſuch, that there is ground to hope what they have done herein is through want of Light, Miſapprehenſion, or the like <hi>Infirmity;</hi> we may then conclude that the groſneſs, wilfulneſs, or whatſoever may make thoſe Actions more than an <hi>Infirmity</hi> in any other <hi>Conformiſt,</hi> muſt ariſe only from the internal frame or badneſs of the Mind and Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for externally they are the ſame. If ſo, then it is nothing at all to us; to them it is, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.27. for in reſpect of the lawfulneſs of our joyning with the adminiſtration, or unlawfulneſs, whether it be done with a better or worſe mind, is not obſervable by us; outward and viſible Sins only pollute others that be in relation. If Envy, Pride, Hypocriſy, or the like Evils of the Mind did ſo, we ſhould be conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guilty of other Men's Sins, and without Remedy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 2.</label> What-ever Sins are in the Perſon as to himſelf, they are to me but as Sins of Infirmity, that is, ſuch Evils adhering to the Worſhip as I have no power to prevent; I may and ought to mourn for ſuch mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as for my own Infirmities, but avoid them I cannot without I avoid the Duty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 2.</label> There is much Error mingled with the few Truths they preach, as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, Arminianiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There are alſo invective Reflections, <hi>yea,</hi> railings againſt the People of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 1.</label> What is <hi>morally</hi> Good, will bear the mixture of a great deal of Evil, and yet retain its Goodneſs ſtill: the Goodneſs being from God, who is a greater Good, than Satan or Sin, is an Evil.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 2.</label> We cannot expect from Men of ordinary Gifts, that Truth be preached without the mixture of Errors more or leſs: We <hi>know but in part, therefore are to prove all things, and hold faſt that which is good, Heb.</hi> 5.14. A Saint, as other Creatures, though weak and newly born, hath a taſte of what is Food ſuitable, and what ſincere.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 3.</label> As for thoſe intemperate Expreſſions and Reflections on the People of God, I confeſs it is ſad; but were there not ſuch againſt <hi>Paul</hi> and his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179944:6"/>Party? <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.15. yet notwithſtanding they are to be heard, even by the ſame Perſons they enveighed againſt for the Truth's ſake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 3.</label> The Lives of moſt of our <hi>Conformiſts</hi> are vile and abominable, full of Pride, Covetouſneſs, Luxury, Drunkenneſs: How can we expect a Bleſſing on their Labours, though they preach Truth and good Things?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 1.</label> The mixtures in Sermons are neareſt; the Irregularities of their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the next; the Sins of their Converſations fartheſt from their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and therefore have leſs efficacy at ſuch a diſtance to preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 2.</label> It's God's Word, and not their own, they preach. Truth is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the Lord for its own ſake, and his whoſe it is. When Chriſt bleſſed his Diſciple; with the promiſe of his preſence, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Lo I am with you always, even to the end of the World;</hi> it is to be applyed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to their <hi>Doctrine</hi> than <hi>Perſons:</hi> for they were ſometimes left to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Infirmities in their lives, and they lived not <hi>to the end of the World.</hi> If it be not Truth, though an Angel from Heaven bring it, no Bleſſing will come with it; but if it be <hi>Chriſt</hi> that is preached, whoever is the Inſtrument, there is matter of hope and rejoicing, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some preached Chriſt who were not ſincere, though at the ſame time others who were blameleſs preached the ſame Truths. <hi>What then?</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> verſ. 18. <hi>Notwithſtanding, every way Chriſt is preached, and therein do I rejoice, and will rejoice.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Peter</hi> mentions, they <hi>ſed the Flock,</hi> the Flock then heard them, and were inſtructed by them: yet we are told thoſe Miniſters were <hi>Covetous, Ambitious,</hi> took up their Miniſtry for <hi>filthy Lucres-ſake,</hi> and were <hi>Lords over God's Heritage.</hi> More cannot be objected againſt our <hi>Miniſters</hi> that <hi>Conform,</hi> than might againſt the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s time; either in reſpect of their <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which was loaden with <hi>Traditions;</hi> their <hi>Standing,</hi> which was not according to <hi>Law;</hi> their <hi>lives,</hi> which were <hi>vicious:</hi> yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> not only <hi>permits,</hi> but <hi>requires</hi> us to attend the Truths they deliver.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>Conſideration III.</head>
               <head type="sub">About <hi>partaking</hi> with another Man's ſins.</head>
               <p>This ariſeth from ſome <hi>ſpecial relation,</hi> as a <hi>moral touch:</hi> which is either in reſpect to the Perſon tranſgreſſing, or the Sin it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our <hi>Relation</hi> to Perſons may either be, 1. <hi>Tranſient,</hi> or <hi>Occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi> For a Man becomes guilty with him that ſinneth, by <hi>applanding, approving,</hi> or <hi>encouraging</hi> him in his Sin, <hi>John</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32. and in ſome caſes by <hi>ſilence,</hi> being preſent when ſome groſs Sin is openly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179944:7"/>commited. Or, 2. our <hi>Relation</hi> may be <hi>ſet</hi> and <hi>ſtated,</hi> either <hi>Civil,</hi> as between Parents and Children, Maſters and Servants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This will not be much to our purpoſe: or <hi>Sacred, viz.</hi> that <hi>ſetled Relation</hi> that ariſeth from <hi>Goſpel-Communion,</hi> as in <hi>particular Churches</hi> between Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Members, and one Member with another. By virtue of this <hi>Relation,</hi> Sins are tranſmitted from one to another with the greateſt celerity and efficacy; <hi>A little Leaven leaveneth the whole Lump.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Evil</hi> of another, and that <hi>Duty</hi> we join in, may ſo <hi>relate,</hi> as I may partake of his Evil, though I act nothing with him but what is a Duty on my part. Receiving of Rents and Tenantſhip are ſo nearly related, that if the Perſon with whom I partake thus, have forfeited his Tenantſhip, and of right is no Tenant, yet by my accepting of Rent from him, I make him one notwithſtanding his forfeiture. To exerciſe a Judicial Act, relates ſo much to the Perſon legally conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Judg, that if I ſubmit my Cauſe to him that is not ſo, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, I ſin againſt my own Liberty. In each of theſe what I do is good, but <hi>partakes ſomewhat</hi> with the evil of another. In our <hi>Spiritual</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, that is a full inſtance, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.18. <hi>They that eat of the Sacrifice, partake of the Altar;</hi> that is, from the <hi>Relation</hi> and <hi>Connexion</hi> betwixt the Altar and the Gift. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.19. <hi>The Altar ſanctifieth the Gift.</hi> It is either not a Sacrifice, or not a Lawful Sacrifice, but by reaſon of the <hi>Altar.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For Application to the Caſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. My being preſent, and hearing of a <hi>Conformiſt,</hi> is no <hi>Approbation</hi> of the evil of his <hi>Conformity,</hi> and ſo no <hi>occaſional</hi> or <hi>tranſient Relation</hi> is raiſed thereby. <hi>Approbation</hi> is an act of the Mind or Heart; It is not ſhewed to him or others by me, until it be <hi>expreſſed outwardly</hi> by my Words or Geſtures which I have not in this caſe any occaſion to do; his Evil being done elſewhere, and formerly, and not in our preſence that now hear him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nor is there any <hi>ſet</hi> or <hi>ſtanding Relation</hi> between him and me, though he preach and I hear him conſtantly: This creates no <hi>Church-fellowſhip</hi> or <hi>Communion.</hi> To inſtruct and learn, is an <hi>humane</hi> or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral converſe, and differs not from teaching or learning any other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, though the ſubject Matter I hear be Divine. It's true, by the addition of a <hi>ſpecial</hi> Inſtitution, it becomes a <hi>Church-Ordinance:</hi> ſo <hi>giving of Alms, viſiting of the Sick,</hi> and the like, which are Actions of <hi>common</hi> Humanity, when brought under a <hi>ſpecial</hi> Inſtitution, do thereby become as much <hi>Church</hi>-Ordinances as <hi>Preaching,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14. <hi>What fellowſhip hath Light with Darkneſs? or a Believer with an Infidel?</hi> that is, in <hi>reſpect to Church-Communion</hi> and <hi>Fellowſhip,</hi> there is none: yet a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179944:7"/>
                     <hi>Believer</hi> and an <hi>Infidel</hi> may Preach and Hear, may Teach and be Taught, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. For any ſpecial <hi>Tincture</hi> derived from his Evil to the Duty we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form with him; it muſt be either from the Sins of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> or his <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination:</hi> The former hath been ſpoken to. As for the evil of his <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> it relates not to his Preaching, by any ſuch near aliance, as that the one may not be done without the other. <hi>It is the duty of all Chriſtians</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ames</hi>) <hi>to do their utmoſt to advance the Kingdom of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to teach others the Knowledg of God.</hi> Why may not a Man Preach and Inſtruct others, if he be able, by <hi>word of Mouth,</hi> as well as by <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Printing</hi> Theological Diſcourſes? This latter was never queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by any ſober Man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>OBJECTIONS ANSWERED.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 1.</label> My preſence at ſuch Mens Preaching, if I be ſilent and give no teſtimony againſt them, will be an encouragement to their way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 1.</label> If I had no other <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>apparent</hi> reaſon for my being preſent, it might be ſo interpreted; but my preſence <hi>relates,</hi> and ought ſo to be judged, unto the <hi>Word Preached.</hi> If I be preſent in ſome conſecreated place, adorned with Images, to hear a Sermon, my preſence ought not to be interpreted a <hi>Countenancing</hi> thoſe <hi>Superſtitions,</hi> but the <hi>Preaching of Gods Word.</hi> When the <hi>Preaching of Chriſt,</hi> and a <hi>malitious Spirit,</hi> was in one Man, <hi>Pauls</hi> rejoycing at the one, was no Countenancing of the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 2.</label> We do not ſo eaſily derive guilt or pollution by being preſent, or in the Company of Sinners, though we do not teſtify againſt them, when they are not in <hi>Spiritual Communion</hi> with us. <hi>A little Leaven leaveneth the whole Lump,</hi> but no more. The <hi>Contagion</hi> goeth no further than the <hi>Relation.</hi> The Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9. layeth down clearly this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from that Verſe to the end. He ſpeaks of <hi>Judging,</hi> that is, <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring</hi> of others, that we may prevent partaking with them in their Guilt. By <hi>Judging</hi> we are to underſtand not only the <hi>Cenſure</hi> it ſelf, but the <hi>telling our Brother,</hi> the <hi>reproving, convincing,</hi> and other private Duties in relation thereunto, and <hi>avoiding</hi> their Company afterwards: and it is applied with diſtinction of Perſons in reſpect of their relation to us. There are <hi>Fornicators of this World, ver.</hi> 10. and ſuch <hi>are without, ver.</hi> 12. Now there is not that Obligation lying upon us to reprove their Sins, as <hi>if a Brother be a Fornicator, ver.</hi> 11. In ſome caſes we may be ſilent, and leave the former to the <hi>Judgment of God, ver.</hi> 13. But in no caſe if he be a Brother.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:179944:8"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 3.</label> To <hi>Reprove</hi> or give <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt an evil, is a tender Duty, and we may eaſily miſcarry, if the rules thereof be not ſtrictly obſerved. 1. Eſpecially, if publick, in the Face of a Congregation come together peaceably to worſhip God. 2. And the Perſon an Elder, at leaſt ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted generally by the Congregation. 3. The Sin alſo muſt be a <hi>groſs</hi> Sin, and apparant ſo to the Aſſembly. But if it be doubtful, as in our Caſe, whether it be a Sin, or ſuch a Sin; whether committed upon the place, or formerly, we know not where, nor how long ſince: if poſſibly he hath repented of it, or is able to clear himſelf at leaſt from the groſneſs of it: I ſay, in ſuch a caſe, were he a <hi>Brother,</hi> and in this <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> I have no <hi>Call</hi> to reprove, or give a publick teſtimony, in ſuch time or place eſpecially.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 4.</label> This Objection renders not my coming to hear, an Evil, but my not reproving. I am the rather bound to come, for I have hereby not only an opportunity to receive, but to do good, if ſuch reproving be a duty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 2.</label> Ordination and Conformity, and Common Prayers, and Ceremonies, are connexed with Preaching, as one intire Service; by partaking thereof of the the one, we contract the pollution of the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 1.</label> What God himſelf in a <hi>moral</hi> way joyneth together, no Man may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate, only God himſelf: But what God in <hi>Nature</hi> hath joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he gives us leave to ſeparate, as Chaff from Wheat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo likewiſe for what Man joyneth together, eſpecially in the Service of God, and ſuch matters thereof as God hath not required; A <hi>ſet Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> or <hi>ſtinted Form of Prayer</hi> for matter and Words to be uſed (much leſs to be inſeparably joyned with Preaching) is not required by the Lord, nor indeed is there any ſuch neceſſary dependance by our Laws.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 2.</label> 
                     <hi>Ordination</hi> is not ſo <hi>neceſſarily</hi> connexed with Preaching, either by God or Man: Scripture-light mentions <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Hearing</hi> as Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. whereas yet there could be no Ordination; nor are they ſo inſeparably joyned by our Laws: But if they were, it is ſufficient to my Conſcience that God hath not ſo joyned them. Our actings, and the reaſons or grounds of them, are not to be interpreted in Church-Matters by Humane Laws; If they were, it would be difficult to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit in ſome Common-wealths with a good Conſcience. Our living with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Precincts</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Pariſh,</hi> our Laws interpret a being of the ſame <hi>particular Church</hi> with them for all <hi>Church-Ordinances:</hi> but this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179944:8"/>being Mans Law only, we judge our ſelves not ſo neceſſarily involved by our habitation. A Church according to <hi>Scripture</hi> is a <hi>Spiritual Body:</hi> The Limits are part of the eſſence and conſtitution of ſuch a Body, and therefore ought to be <hi>Spiritual</hi> and of the ſame nature, and not meerly <hi>humane,</hi> as is the diviſion of Pariſhes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw. 3.</label> To ſpeak more properly, we cannot ſay nearneſs by an external diſpoſition of things connexeth them any more, than Unity makes kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, or of one Blood. No, it muſt be where there is ſuch a dependency of things, that the being, at leaſtwiſe the <hi>orderly</hi> being, of the one is not without the other. In this Senſe <hi>Baptizing, breaking of Bread,</hi> and other <hi>Ordinances</hi> that relate to, and neceſſarily depend on an Office, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed with it, and ſo our being called thereunto, and inveſted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and if the perſon with whom I partake, be either not in ſuch an Office, or in any apparent diſorderly way, I partake with his Sin: ſo near are theſe Duties related in their <hi>orderly</hi> Adminiſtration. But <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> in a <hi>Providential</hi> way, as by Perſons gifted, and out of their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity adminiſtring to us, or by Proviſion of the Magiſtrate, is altogether of another nature. And though <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Preaching</hi> be joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the vulgar eſteem; yet it's not the voice or ſanction of Man can bring things into a nearer Relation than the Spirit hath ſet them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 3.</label> Why may we not as well go to Common-Prayer?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> If there were no other things to be objected againſt thoſe Prayers, but <hi>Ordination, Conformity,</hi> or other Sins of the Miniſter's, queſtionleſs we may: for we queſtion not to joyn with them in Prayer before or after Sermon, more than with his <hi>Preaching.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Object. 4.</label> Where there is any better Preaching than Ordinary, eſpecially in the City, it is ſo thronged, as by that time Prayers are ended, there is no hearing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> It is one thing to abſtain upon ſuch an account which is <hi>prudential</hi> only, as upon the account of bodily infirmity: another thing to abſtain upon the opinion of unlawfulneſs. Now the thing contended for, is to vindicate the <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> of hearing ſuch Miniſters, notwithſtanding what hath been objected to the contrary, and to deliver us from an Error of very ill conſequence: for this Opinion, <hi>that it is unlawful to hear ſuch Miniſters as have been ſpoken of,</hi> is an error of <hi>very ill</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, in many reſpects.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It puts us upon ſuch ſingularity, as by which we divide in our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179944:9"/>practice, not only from our Brethren of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> perſwaſion, but likewiſe from divers of the ſobereſt Separatiſts. Where a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence neceſſitates, as in many things, to differ from other Godly Brethren on each hand, it is a ſad Providence to have theſe differences increaſed by an <hi>erronious</hi> Conſcience.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Except it be the <hi>reading of Scriptures,</hi> this Ordinance alone, of all other publick Ordinances amongſt us, hath by the good hand of God been kept and continued by our <hi>National</hi> Eſtabliſhment free in it ſelf from all diſputable Mixtures and Impoſitions; and the benefit and fruit of this Publick Miniſtry, hath accordingly been viſibly great, as in any part of the World. Let us fear therefore leſt we our ſelves now by raiſing <hi>groundleſs</hi> ſcruples, lay this as low, as others by their <hi>unwarranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> additions have done the other Publick Ordinances.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In moſt of the miſperſwaſions of theſe latter times, by which Mens Minds have been corrupted, I find in whatſoever otherwiſe they differ one from another, yet in this they agree, that its <hi>unlawful to hear in Publick;</hi> Which I am perſwaded is one conſtant deſign of Satan, in the variety of ways in Religion he hath ſet on Foot by Jeſuites amongſt us. Let us therefore be the more aware of whatſoever tends that way.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Such reaſonings againſt <hi>Hearing,</hi> though they convince not the unlawfulneſs of it, yet they leave ſuch prejudices in the minds of them which are tender, as perplex and render Hearing leſs profitable and edifying, even to thoſe that are perſwaded of its <hi>Lawfulneſs.</hi> To bring the lawfulneſs of known Ordinances under diſpute for ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances affixed, hath even been of great advantage to Satan, whether in ſuch diſputes he prevails or not: For Men are either beaten wholly off from the duty, or perform it with a more remiſs and unſutable Spirit, which lieth more directly in the way to prevent a bleſſing, than the evils of others we ordinarily object. Thoſe diſputes about the <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of the Sabbath, as they have prevailed with many to a <hi>total neglect;</hi> ſo with more to a <hi>remiſs obſervance,</hi> though convinced of it as a <hi>moral</hi> Duty. If for <hi>ſubſtance</hi> the Duty be ſo evident, as not to be liable to a diſpute in it ſelf (as this of Hearing is); then Satan faſtens Scruples about <hi>Circumſtances;</hi> which prevailing, we have as little benefit from the <hi>Ordinance</hi> or Duty, as if it were not.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>
                  <hi>The end of Mr.</hi> Nye's <hi>Reaſons touching the lawfulneſs of hearing the Publick Miniſters.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="religious_treatise">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:179944:9"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
               <p>TO ſtop the Mouths of many, eſpecially thoſe Miniſters that continually from Preſs and Pulpit do maliciouſly, as well as ignorantly, tell the People that the Diſſenters (eſpecially <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi>) do act contrary to their own Principles, in Communicating ſometimes with the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and that they do ſo meerly to qualifie themſelves for an Office, to ſerve a Turn (as they ſpitefully phraſe it) or to ſave themſelves from the penal Laws, I have here inſerted in what follows, the Opinion not only of the <hi>Independents,</hi> but even the <hi>Browniſts</hi> themſelves, many years ſince about this matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="text_of_treatise">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIZ.</hi> A TREATISE of the Lawfulneſs of Hearing the Publick Miniſters in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Penned by that Learned and Reverend Divine, Mr. JOHN ROBINSON, late Paſtor to the Engliſh Church of God at <hi>Leyden:</hi> Printed there in the Year 1634, and now publiſhed for Publick Satisfaction.</head>
               <p>AS they that affect alienation from others, make their differences as great, and the adverſe Opinion or Practice as odious as they can; thereby to further their deſired victory over them, and to harden themſelves, and their ſide againſt them: So on the contrary, they, who deſire peace and accord, both interpret things in the beſt part that reaſonably they can, and ſeek how and where they may find any lawful door of entry into accord and agreement with others. Of which latter number I profeſs my ſelf (by the Grace of God) both a Companion and Guide: ſpecially in regard of my Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Country-men, to whom God hath tied me in ſo many inviolable bonds: accounting it a Croſs, that I am in any particular compelled to diſſent from them; but a benefit, and matter of rejoycing, when I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179944:10"/>can, in any thing with good a Conſcience unite with them, in matter, if not in manner; or, where it may be, in both. And this Affection, the Lord and my Conſcience are my Witneſſes, I have always nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my Breaſt, even when I ſeemed furtheſt drawn from them. And ſo all that have taken knowledg of my Courſe can teſtifie with me, and how I have ſtill oppoſed in others, and repreſſed in mine own (to my power) all ſower zeal againſt, and peremptory rejection of ſuch, as whoſe Grace: challenged better uſe and reſpect from all Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>And in teſtimony of mine affection this way, and for the freeing of mine own Conſcience, and information of other Mens, I have penned this Diſcourſe, tending to prove <hi>the hea<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ng of the Word of God preached by the Mi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſters <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the Church of</hi> Engl<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>n and apply the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>d in caſes neceſſary for all, of all Sec<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s or ſorts of Ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="8 letters">
                        <desc>〈8 letters〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>ity and occaſion of ſo doing: though ſequeſtring themſelv<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll C<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>nion with the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical Order there eſtabliſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three ſorts of oppoſites I make account to meet withal. The firſt of them, who truly deſire, and carefully endeavour to have their whole courſe both in Religion, and otherwiſe, framed by the holy and right Zeal of God's Word, either for their confirmation in the Truth; or Reformation, wherein, through humane frailty they ſtep aſide. And unto them eſpecially I direct this my Diſcourſe: begging at his hands who is <hi>the Father of Lights, and from whom cometh down every good and perfect Gift,</hi> for them, as for my ſelf, that as he hath given us to ſet our Faces towards Heaven, and to <hi>ſeek him with the whole Heart, ſo he would not ſuffer us to wander from his Commandments,</hi> to the right hand or to the left.</p>
               <p>A ſecond ſort is of them, whoſe tender and ſcrupulous Conſcience, makes them fearful, and jealous of every thing, which hath in it the leaſt appearance of evil; leſt coming too near it, they be defiled by it, one way or other. This their godly Zeal, and tenderneſs of Heart is to be loved of all Men, and cheriſhed by all good means. Only ſuch are to be intreated, for their own good, to take knowledge of a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on moſt uſeful for their direction, in things lawful in their kind, and good in their right uſe. Of which ſome are only naturally good in their kind, but not ſimply commanded of God, as to get, and keep the riches and credit of the World; to enjoy outward Peace, or other bodily Comfort. Others are morally good in their kind, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God, as to hear the Word of God, obey the Magiſtrate, and the like. Now in things of the former ſort, it is very requiſit (conſidering both their Nature and ours) that we keep a jealous Eye, and ſtrait
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179944:10"/>Hand over our ſelves, and our ways. For them, they are not in their kind enjoyed as the other: neither do the Scriptures any where require of Men, to be rich, or the like: as they do to hear Gods Word, obey Authority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And for our ſelves we are prone, and in danger to over-ſtrain for the getting and enjoying of them, as being naturally pleaſing good things. So as if out of a godly jealouſie over our Hearts towards them, we keep not our ſelves from going too near the ſide, for the getting or keeping of them; we ſhall by one ſtorm of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or other, be blown into the ditch of Sin and Deſtruction. But now, for the practice and performance of Duties ſimply moral, and commanded in their kind, as is the hearing of God's Word, ſpecially by God's People, we ought to ſtrain to the uttermoſt, and to go as near the wind as may be; ſeeing nothing but apparent Sin in the way can excuſe the withdrawing from it, when occaſion of enjoying it is offered. O that there were not to be found ſome, who being very ſcrupulous of coming near to any thing amiſs in outward Ordinances, or to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon failing in them; yet make no ſcruple of complying, and conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the World ſo far in the eager purſuit of Worldly Profits, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate uſe of worldly Delights, and fulfilling the Luſts of the World and Fleſh dwelling in them, as that there appears ſcarce an hair's-breadth of difference between them, and meer Worldlings which know not God. Which latter Evils are both worſe in themſelves, as being expreſly condemned by the Law of God, and Light of Nature; and more odious in the perſons, as being more perſonal, free, and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary than thoſe in the other, to which they are carried by the violent Current of the Times.</p>
               <p>A third ſort of Oppoſits I make account to meet with, more untracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than the former, and more vehemently bent againſt the things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by me, out of prejudice and paſſion, than the other by ſcruple of Conſcience, or ſhew of Reaſon. To them I can hardly ſay any thing; (it not being their manner to reade, or willingly to hear that which croſſeth their prejudices) yet ſomething I muſt ſay touching them, out of the woful experience of many years taken of them, though not much (I thank the Lord) amongſt them unto whom I have miniſtred.</p>
               <p>Some of theſe I have found carried with ſo exceſſive admiration of ſome former Guides in their courſe, as they think it half Hereſy to call into queſtion any of their Determinations, or Practices. We muſt not think that only the Phariſees of old, or Papiſts of later times, are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly addicted to <hi>the Tradition of the Elders, and Authority of the Church.</hi> In all Sects there are divers (eſpecially of the weaker ſort, who being the leſs real in their conceptions, are the more perſonal) that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179944:11"/>rather chuſe to follow the path of blind Tradition, if beaten by ſome ſuch fore-goers as they admire, than the right way of God's Word by others, to be ſhewed them afterwards.</p>
               <p>Some again are as much addicted to themſelves as the former to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others; conceiving in effect, though they will not profeſs it, the ſame of their own heads, which the Papiſts do of their Head the Pope, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that they cannot erre, or be deceived: and this ſpecially in ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as for which they have ſuffered troubles and afflictions formerly; and ſo having bought them dear, they value them highly. But it is too Merchant-like to ſtrive to over-ſell a thing, which we have formerly over-bought: We muſt <hi>buy the Truth, and ſell it not</hi> at any rate; but muſt account nothing either true or good, according to the valuation which we have ſet upon it, but God.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a third ſort highly advancing a kind of privative Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Religion; and who bend their force rather to the weakning of other Men in their courſes, than to the building up of themſelves in their own; and in truth, rather to ſeparation from Men not only in evil, but even in that which is good, for ſome other evil conceived in them, than to Union with God and his People in his holy Ordinances: and half imagining that they draw near enough to God, if they can withdraw far enough from other Men. Great Zeal they have againſt the falſe Church, Miniſtry and Worſhip ſo being, or by them conceived ſo to be; and againſt any appearing evil in the true, but little for that which is true and good, as their practice manifeſts: But Evil is as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Evil, as Good is to Evil; and ſo is that Zeal plainly carnal, which carries a Man further againſt Evil, than for Good; ſeeing no Evil is ſo evil, as Good is good.</p>
               <p>Fourthly; There are ſome to be found ſo ſowred with moodineſs and diſcontentment, as they become unſociable, and almoſt <hi>Lukanthropoi;</hi> Werewolfs, as they ſpeak; if they ſee nothing lamentable, they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to lament: if they take contentment in any, it is in them alone whom they find diſcontented: if they reade any Books, they are only Invec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, eſpecially againſt Publick States, and their Governours. All things tending to accord and union any manner of way, are unwelcome unto them. They have their Portion in <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s Bleſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.12.</p>
               <p>Laſtly; There want not ſome, who (as <hi>Jehu</hi> in his fierce marching, covered his Ambition, Cruelty, and Zeal for his own Houſe, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of Zeal for God's) think to cover and palliate their both groſſer, and more proper and perſonal Corruptions, under a furious March, not only againſt the Failings, but the Perſons alſo failing, of Infirmity in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Church-Order and Ordinances. Who if they were well acquainted,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179944:11"/>and duly affected with their own, both more voluntary, and greater Sins, would ſlack their <hi>Jehu</hi>'s Peace, yea turn their Courſe, tho not to walk with others in Evil (which God forbid) yet to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and accommodate themſelves unto them, in that which is good, ſo far as poſſibly they could obſerve any way by the Lord opened unto them. I could inſtance in, and name divers particular Perſons mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly grown out of kind, this way. But that Courſe I leave unto them, who rather deſire the diſgracing, than the bettering of them againſt whom they deal: Or perhaps conceive in their leavened Hearts that there is no other way of bettering, ſpecially Perſons of mean Condition, than by diſgracing them. But <hi>let not my Soul come in their Secret, in whoſe Habitations are</hi> ſuch <hi>Inſtruments of Cruelty.</hi> Gen. 49.5, 6.</p>
               <p>Theſe things thus premiſed, the Objections follow, which I have either heard from others, or can conceive of my ſelf moſt colourable againſt the Practice by me propounded. And they are of two ſorts: Some of them are framed upon Suppoſition, that the Miniſters in that Church are in themſelves lawful, and of God: but now yet to be heard by reaſon of the Abuſes, and Evils to be found in their Miniſtrations. Others withdraw herein (and thoſe the more) upon the contrary Suppoſition: To wit, that the very Order and Conſtitution of that Church and Miniſtry is Papal, and unlawful. Now the Examination of the Grounds of the one or other I will not in this place meddle with: but (though both cannot be true) will for the ſatisfying of the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawers on both Parts, grant for the preſent, to either Part their Ground, and ſo examine diſtinctly what Exceptions they can or do build thereupon.</p>
               <p>But firſt, for the former: Suppoſing a Church and the Miniſtry there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of eſſentially lawful, it cannot but be lawful for the Members of other Churches in general Union and Aſſociation with it, to communicate therewith, in things lawful, and lawfully done: ſeeing the end of Union is Communion. God hath in vain united Perſons, and States to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, if they may in nothing communicate together. But he who would have us <hi>receive the weak in Faith,</hi> whom <hi>God hath received,</hi> would not have us refuſe the Fellowſhip of Churches in that which is good, for any Weakneſs in them, of one ſort or other. And this we have ſo plainly, and plentifully commended unto us both by the Prophets, yea, by Chriſt himſelf, in the Jewiſh Church; and Apoſtles, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Men in the firſt Chriſtian Churches; in which many Errors, and Evils of all kinds were more than manifeſt: and the ſame oft-times both ſo far ſpread, and deeply rooted, as the reforming of them was rather to be wiſhed, than hoped for: As that no place is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179944:12"/>left for doubting in that caſe by any, who deſire to follow their holy Steps in Faith towards God, and Charity towards Men, and effectual Deſire of their own Edification.</p>
               <p>The Objections of the former ſort follow.</p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>There is danger of being ſeduced, and miſled by the Errors taught in the Aſſemblies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. We muſt not loſe the Benefit of many main Truths taught, for danger of ſome few Errors, ſpecially in leſſer matters. This were to fear the Devil, more than to truſt God. 2. There were in the Jewiſh Church in Chriſt's time, and in divers of the Apoſtolical Churches afterwards, more and greater Errors taught, than are in any, or all the Churches in <hi>England;</hi> of which alſo there are not a few; which if their Miniſters did as fully and faithfully teach and practiſe all Truths, as they keep themſelves carefully from Errors, might compare in this Buſineſs, with any reformed Church in <hi>Europe.</hi> 3. This Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception hath its weight againſt the hearing of Prieſts and Jeſuits, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by the weaker ſort, and leſs able to diſcern of things that differ: But not againſt many Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>He that in any thing partakes with that Church in which Sins known are ſuffered unreformed, partakes in all the Sins of that Church: as he that ſwears by the Altar, ſwears by the Offerings upon it which it ſanctifies,</hi> Mat. 23.19, 20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I partake not in the Sins of any, how great or manifeſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Sins be, or how near unto me ſoever the Perſons be; except the ſame Sins either be committed, or remain unreformed by my Fault: Otherwiſe Chriſt our Lord had been inwrapped in the Guilt of a world of Sins in the Jewiſh Church, with which Church he communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in God's Ordinances, living and dying a Member thereof. If my Brother ſin a ſcandalous Sin, and I by juſt order make Complaint there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the Church, I have done my Duty; It appertains to the Church to excommunicate him, if he repent not; but not to me, except (Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like) I would make my ſelf the Church. I am guilty of the Evil in the Commonwealth and Family, for redreſſing whereof I do not my duty in my place: which if I do in the Church as I can, I am free from the Sins done and ſuffered there; which Sins and Evils I can no more be ſaid to ſuffer (wanting power to reform them) than to ſuffer it to blow or rain, becauſe I hinder it not.</p>
               <p>But the proof of the Aſſertion from <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. is of admirable device. How doth the Church ſanctify the Sin of the Sinner, as the Altar doth the Offering of the Offerer? The Altar makes that to become actually an Offering, or holy Gift, which before was not an Offering actually,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179944:12"/>but only Gold, Silver, or other materials. So doth not the Church make any Man's Sin to become his Sin, which it was not before, but only ſuffers the Sin that was. But to ſtrain the ſtrings of this imagined pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to make them meet; and to ſuppoſe the Church in a ſenſe to be as the Altar; yet this only follows thereupon, that, as he who par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes with the Altar in the upholding of the Offering, partakes with the Offering: So he that partakes with the Church in the upholding of any Evil, hath his part in the Evil alſo.</p>
               <p>And this I grant willingly: but deny, as a moſt vain imagination, that every one that partakes with a Church in things lawful, joyns with it in upholding the things unlawful to be found in it. Chriſt our Lord joyned with the Jewiſh Church in things lawful, and yet upheld no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unlawful in it.</p>
               <p>Object. 3. <hi>But this courſe of Hearing will offend weak Brethren, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the lawfulneſs of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It will offend more, and many of them weaker, and that more grievouſly, if it be not performed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is an Offence taken, and not given; ſeeing the thing is in it ſelf good in its kind, commanded by God; and in that particular, by Men in Authority; and directly tending to my Edification: and not like unto eating of Fleſh, or drinking of Wine, or the like things of indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent nature, and left to my free liberty to uſe, or not to uſe.</p>
               <p>And theſe are the principal <hi>Objections</hi> upon the former Grounds: They upon the latter follow.</p>
               <p>There is in the hands of many, a Treatiſe publiſhed by a Man of Note, containing <hi>certain Reaſons to prove it unlawful to hear, or have Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Communion with the preſent Miniſtry of the Church of England.</hi> This hath been anſwered, but indeed ſophiſtically, and in paſſion: Neither hath the Anſwerer much regarded what he ſaid or unſaid, ſo he might gainſay his Adverſary. With that Anſwer was joyned another, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to my ſelf, and the ſame doubled, pretending to prove <hi>Publick Communion upon Private:</hi> but not preſſing at all, in the body of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, that Conſequence; but proceeding upon other Grounds, and in truth, conſiſting of a continued Equivocation in the terms, <hi>Publick, Licence, Government, Miniſtry,</hi> and the like; drawn to another ſenſe than either I intended them, or than the matter in queſtion will permit. Whereas he that will refute another, ſhould religiouſly take, and hold to his Adverſaries meaning. And if in any particular it be not ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet down, ſhould ſpell it as it were out of his words. But it is no
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179944:13"/>new thing, even for Learned and Godly Men, to take more than lawful Liberty in dealing with them againſt whom they have the Advantage of the Times favouring them, like the Wind on their Backs. But God forbid I ſhould follow them herein: I will on the contrary uſe all plainneſs and ſimplicity, as in the ſight of God, that ſo I may make the naked Truth appear as it is to the Chriſtian Reader's Eye what in me lieth.</p>
               <p>And for the Treatiſe mentioned, it muſt be obſerved, how both in the Title and body of the Book, the Author confounds as one <hi>hearing of</hi> and <hi>having Spiritual Communion with the Miniſtery,</hi> &amp;c. Which as it is true of ſuch as ſtand in ſpiritual and political Church-Union with a Church, and the Miniſtry thereof, who accordingly have Church-Communion in the publick Acts and Exerciſes of that Church; ſo is it not true of others, which are not Members of, nor in Eccleſiaſtical Union and Combination with the ſaid Church.</p>
               <p>For the better clearing of things, let us in a few words conſider di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly of Religious Actions, according to the ſeveral Ranks in which they may rightly and orderly be ſet. Some ſuch Actions are Religious only, as they are performed by Religious Perſons. And of this ſort is Hearing (and ſo Reading) of God's Word. The Scriptures teach, and all confeſs, that Hearing of the Word of God goes before Faith: <hi>For Faith comes by Hearing,</hi> as by an outward means, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 10.7.) Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then being before Faith, and Faith before all other Acts of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion inward or outward; it muſt needs follow, that Hearing is not ſimply, or of it ſelf, a work of Religion, and ſo not of Religious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. Hearing is properly, and of it ſelf, a natural Action, though it be the hearing the very Word of God. And I call it a natural Action in it ſelf, in a double reſpect: Firſt, for that the Light of Nature tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth every Man to hear and liſten to another, that can and will teach and inform him in any thing for his good, divine or humane. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for that a meer natural Man, <hi>Jew, Turk, Infidel,</hi> or <hi>Idolater,</hi> law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully may, yea neceſſarily ought to hear God's Word; that ſo of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral he may become ſpiritual.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond rank, I place Preaching and Prayer; which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Acts religious and ſpiritual; as being to be performed the one by a Gift, the other by a Grace of God's Spirit. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16, 17. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8. <hi>John.</hi> 9.31.</p>
               <p>Of a third ſort is the Paricipation in the Sacraments; which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily at leaſt requires a Memberſhip in ſome particular and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Church in the Participant, they being publick Church-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:179944:13"/>
               <p> In a fourth Order I ſet the Power of Suffrage, and Voice-giving in electing of Officers, and ceſuring of Offenders; for which there is requiſite an Intereſt of the Perſon ſo voting, in that particular Church, as a Member thereof.</p>
               <p>Of the laſt ſort is the Miniſtration of Sacraments, which requires, with the reſt fore-mentioned, a publick State of Miniſtry in the Perſon adminiſtring them.</p>
               <p>Now for Preaching by ſome, and Hearing by others (which two al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways go together) they may be, and oft are performed without any Religious or Spiritual Communion at all paſſing between the Perſons Preaching or Hearing.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Paul</hi> preached to the <hi>ſuperſtitious Athenians,</hi> ſhall we conceive he had Spiritual Communion with that Heatheniſh Aſſembly? How much leſs had they Spiritual and Religious Communion with him, who performed not ſo much as a Religious Work in their hearing? As God gave any of them to believe, they came into inviſible, or inwardly Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Perſonal Communion with him: as they came to make Perſonal Manifeſtation and Declaration of their Faith, they came into out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Perſonal Communion with him: Laſtly, as they came to joyn in, or unto ſome particular Church, into Church-Communion with him, elſe not. So when <hi>there comes into the Church-Aſſembly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers, Heathens, Turks, Jews, Atheiſts, Excommunicates,</hi> Men of all Religions, Men of none at all, and there hear; what ſpiritual Communion have they with the Church or State of the Teacher, or one with another, either in regard of the nature of the Act done, or by God's Ordination and Inſtitution? Hearing ſimply is not appointed of God to be a Mark, and Note either of Union in the ſame Faith, or Order amongſt all that hear; or of differencing of Chriſtians from no Chriſtians, or of Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers from no Members of the Church; as the Sacraments are Notes of both in the Participants. The hearing of the Word of God is not ſo incloſed by any hedg or ditch, divine or humane, made about it, but lies in common for all, for the good of all.</p>
               <p>The particular Objections follow.</p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>No Man may ſubmit his Conſcience to be wrought upon by an unlawful and Antichriſtian Miniſtry: neither hath God promiſed, or doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford any Bleſſing upon it; neither can any have the ſanctified uſe thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It cannot be ſaid properly that the Office of the Miniſtry works upon the Conſcience of the Hearer. The Office only gives power and charge to the Teacher, to teach in ſuch or ſuch a Church-ſtate.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179944:14"/>And as it reſides in the Perſon of the Officer alone; ſo the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion (lawful or unlawful) which any hath with it, is in regard of the lawful or unlawful Eccleſiaſtical Relation and Union foregoing between the Perſons; and not in any working of the Office upon the Conſcience of any. Secondly, Though God bleſs not the unlawful Office of the Miniſtry, which is not of himſelf: yet he may and doth bleſs the Truths taught by the Officer, which are of himſelf, and from Heaven. To deny this of many in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is (<hi>Balaam</hi>-like) to curſe, where God would have us to bleſs.</p>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>To hear ſuch a Miniſter, is to honour, approve, and uphold his Office of Miniſtry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If this be ſimply true; then when the heatheniſh <hi>Athenians</hi> heard <hi>Paul</hi> preach: or when an Unbeliever comes into the Church-Aſſembly, and hears the Preacher, he approves, honours, and upholds the Office of the Miniſtry, which what it means, he is altogether ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant.</p>
               <p>If any reply: <hi>We know the Miniſtry of the Church to be as it is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer: That the knowing of it makes not our act the more or leſs an act of Approbation. If I do an Act wherein I indeed approve of a thing, if I know the thing, I really approve of it upon Knowledg; if I know it not, I really approve of it, but ignorantly. 2. If I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the Office ſimply, becauſe I hear the Officer preach, then I much more approve of all the Doctrines which he delivers, becauſe I hear him deliver them. If the latter ſeems unreaſonable, ſo is the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer much more, except I be in Church-Communion with the Officer, and then indeed I really approve of his Office, as I alſo do of his Doctrine, if it be according to the Confeſſion of Faith made by me; for then I am in former Union with him in the one or other, and ſo have Communion in the Acts thereof. If this were a good ground, that every one approves of the Evil done in matter or manner, where he is preſent, none could live with a good Conſcience in the Society of Men upon Earth. Perſons ſo minded are beſt alone; for with others they will keep no Peace, no not with themſelves neither, if they be true to their own Grounds. But they plainly balk themſelves in their Courſes, either in weakneſs of Judgment, or partiality of Affection, or throught want of due Conſideration of their Ways.</p>
               <p>Object. 3. <hi>By this then it ſeems a Man may be preſent at any act of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and do as others do that practiſe Idolatry, yet not approve of it. And ſo the three Nobles in <hi>Daniel</hi> needed not to have put themſelves upon ſuch Pikes of Danger as they did, for not falling down as others did in the Place.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:179944:14"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. In preaching the Truths of the Goſpel no Idolatrous Act is performed, as there was. 2. It muſt be known, that Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation is properly in the Heart, and only the manifeſtation of Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation in outward Geſture, Speech or Writing: Both the one and other are evil, if the thing be evil. But here it muſt be conſidered, that I may in ſome caſes do the ſame outward Act which others do, and wherein they manifeſt their Approbation of Idolatry or other Evil, and yet I be free in Truth and Deed from all ſuch Approbation and Stain thereof. The <hi>Jews</hi> after Chriſt's Death, and <hi>the taking away</hi> and aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the legal <hi>Ordinances</hi> thereby, circumciſed their Infants, and frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Temple for Purification, and other <hi>Moſaical</hi> Ceremonies as parts of God's Worſhip, and ſtill remaining of Divine Inſtitution. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo <hi>circumciſed</hi> Timothy, <hi>entred the Temple for Purification,</hi> and yet did not approve any manner or way of the Error and Evil in the Jewiſh Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers. To come nearer home: it is the Cuſtom in Popiſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, that all that paſs by a Croſs, muſt in honour of it, leave it on the Right-hand, as they may be reaſon of the placing of it, coming or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Now if I ride with others that way, I may do the thing that they do, and keep Company with them, and yet not honour the Croſs as they do. It is, beſides the former, the manner that ſuch as ſo paſs a Croſs, ſhould in further honour, put off their Hat to the ſaid Croſs. But if I do this alſo, I plainly manifeſt an Approbation of the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. The reaſon of the Difference is, becauſe I have another juſt Cauſe to do the former thing, namely to keep on with my Company, but have no juſt cauſe of the latter. But now, ſuppoſe that at the very place where the Croſs ſtands, I meet with ſome Friend or other, to whom I owe that civil Reſpect of uncovering my Head; I may then do that lawfully alſo upon the former Ground. So, if I had juſt and reaſonable cauſe either of coming or ſtanding by the Magiſtrate (to whom I owe this Civil Honour) whilſt he is performing ſome Act of Idolatry in the Streets, or elſe-where; I might upon the ſame Ground, go or ſtand uncovered by him without juſt Blame. To apply theſe things to the Objection moved, ſeeing no other Cauſe could reſonably be conceived of the King's commanding ſuch a thing, or of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the thing at his Commandment, ſave the worſhipping of the Idol; they in ſo doing could not have eſcaped the juſt blame of Idolatry: But now I have juſt Cauſes more than one of my Hearing, and amongſt the reſt my Edification; and therefore cannot be challenged therein to approve of the Miniſters ſtate or ſtanding. Beſides that, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly anſwered, here is no Idolatrous Act performed.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:179944:15"/>
               <p> Object. 4. <hi>He that hears them preach, hears them as Miniſters of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and as ſent by the Biſhops, and ſo in hearing them, hears and receives them that ſend them; according to that of our Saviour, He that hears you, hears me; and he that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me; and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me.</hi> Luke 9.16. Joh. 13.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I grant the former part of the Objection, and account the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of it a point of Familiſm, ſeeing the Officers of publick States in the executing of their Offices are to be eſteemed according to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Laws and Orders of thoſe States, and not according to any under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand either Courſe or Intention by themſelves or others. They are heard as they preach, and preach as Miniſters of the Biſhops ſending, and the Pariſhes receiving, to which they are ſent by them. And ſo I profeſs I hear them as the Miniſters of the Biſhop's ſending, and of the Pariſhes ſent to; but not as my Miniſters either ſending, or ſent to, except I be of thoſe Pariſhes, or at leaſt in Eccleſiaſtical Union with them. Every one, whether of a falſe Church, or no Church, or excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated from the Church, that hears me, hears me as the Paſtor of the Church which I ſerve, but not as his Paſtor, I ſuppoſe, nor in way of any his ſpiritual Communion with mine Office of Paſtorſhip. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, By <hi>hearing</hi> and <hi>receiving</hi> there, Chriſt's means properly the <hi>hearking to,</hi> believing and obeying the Doctrine taught by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which many <hi>deſpiſed,</hi> unto whom he oppoſeth the former that <hi>heard</hi> it. Now the Miniſters in the Pariſhes have not the Doctrines of the Goſpel from the Biſhops, as they have their Office; but from God in his Word, and ſo far forth as a Man hears, that is, hearkens to, and <hi>receives</hi> them by receiving it, he ſo far hearkens to and receives Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Object. 5. <hi>Yet ſuch as hear them, have Communion with their Office of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry what in them lies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is, they have no Communion at all with it, if it lie not in them to have any, as it doth not. If I hold up my Hand as high as I can, I touch Heaven with my Finger, what in me lies: Do I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at all touch it? If ſuch think to have, any ſuch Communion, it is their Error and Ignorance, but makes not the thing to be the more, than if they thought not ſo.</p>
               <p>Object. 6. <hi>Is there then no Communion at all between the Teacher, and taught? What Profit then comes there by ſuch Hearing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Church-Officer <hi>feeds the Flock</hi> and <hi>Church over which he is ſet,</hi> as the Object of his Miniſtry; ſuch as come in (being not in Church-Union therewith) hear him ſo doing; and, as a Stander-by, hearing me talk to, or diſpute with another (tho I ſpeak not a word to him)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:179944:15"/>may reap as much, and more Fruit by my Speech, than he to whom I direct it; ſo may and doth it often come to paſs with him that hears the Miniſter feed the Flock whoſe Miniſter he is, tho he be no part of it: He may reap Fruit by hearing him feed his Flock, or ſeeing him miniſter Baptiſm to any Member thereof: Here is Communion only in the effects of the Truths taught. It were Uſurpation in any to partake in a Church-Priviledg (which the Office of Miniſtry is) that were not in a Church-State firſt; and ſo if hearing ſimply imported Church-Communion, none but Church-Members might lawfully hear.</p>
               <p>Object. 7. <hi>In the true Church indeed is Order, that the Church-Covenant go before Church-Communion, but not ſo in the falſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the true Church there may be unlawful Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion without a preceeding Church-Covenant, as well as in the other; to wit, if an Act of Communion (properly) paſs between the Church, and him that is no Church-Member; as for Example, Participation in the Sacraments; but hearing being not properly an Act of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cannot import Communion neceſſarily with the one or other; not otherwiſe then according to a fore-going Church-Union; whereas to partake in the Lord's Supper imports Communion in both lawful in him; that is, a lawful Church-Member, and unlawful in him that is not in ſuch a Church-State.</p>
               <p>Object. 8. <hi>But it is the Order of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>that all that hear, are, and ſo are reputed Members of that Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I deny that there is any ſuch Order; let the Law or Canon either be ſhewed that ſo orders things.</p>
               <p>Excommunicates are permitted to hear Sermons, tho not Divine Service, as they call it. 2. What if there were ſuch an Order? It no more either made or declared me to be a Member there, than doth my dwelling in ſuch or ſuch a Pariſh make me a Member of that Pariſh-Church; which latter is indeed the Law and Order there. If the Church with me ſhould make a Law, Canon, or Order, that all that come in and hear me preach, ſhould thereby become Members of it; we were the more fooliſh in making ſuch an Order, but they never a whit the nearer either for Memberſhip or Communion.</p>
               <p>Object. 9. <hi>He that hears, appears to have Communion with the Church, and Miniſtry, and all Appearance of Evil is to be avoided:</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scripture is not to be underſtood of all that appears Evil to Others, out of an erroneous and deceived Judgment; for then we muſt abſtain from almoſt all Good; ſeeing there are ſome to whom almoſt all Good ſeems Evil; but it is meant either of the Doctrine in <hi>Propheſy,</hi> of which I have ſome probable Suſpicion; of which the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179944:16"/>Apoſtle ſeems properly to ſpeak; or of that which appears Evil to a rightly diſcerning eye. By this imagined Expoſition I might not hire a Houſe in a Pariſh where I were not known: ſeeing thereby I appear a Pariſh-member.</p>
               <p>Object. 10. <hi>None can hear without a Preacher, nor Preach except he be ſent,</hi> Rom. 10.14, 15. <hi>Therefore I cannot lawfully hear him that hath nat a lawful ſending.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That concluſion is neither in Text, nor ſound: I may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully hear him that hath no lawful Calling, as I have formerly ſhewed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle's meaning there, is not to ſhew what is unlawful, but what is impoſſible. It is impoſſible to believe without hearing, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to hear without preaching, and impoſſible to preach without the ſending there intended; that is, without God's gracious work of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in raiſing up of Men, by enabling, and diſopſing them to preach for the effectual calling of the Elect of God, of which he there ſpeaks. If any make a Queſtion, Whether Faith come by the hearing of the Preachers there? It is more queſtionable, whether they themſelves want not Faith, which are ſo barren of Charity, in which true Faith is fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. If Faith come by the Preaching in <hi>England</hi> to any; it follows there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon that ſuch Preachers are ſent in the Apoſtle's ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Object. 11. <hi>The Sheep of Chriſt hear his Voice, but ſtrangers they will not hear.</hi> John 10.3, 8, 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt does not there ſpeak of the outward Hearing, but of the hearkning unto; that is, as he expounds himſelf, ver. 3, 4, 5, 14, 15, 16, 17. of the <hi>knowing</hi> and <hi>beieving</hi> of his Voice, and following it. So Chap. 9. <hi>I told you before, and ye did not hear;</hi> that is, not believe, ver. 27. And, <hi>God hears not Sinners,</hi> ver. 31. that is, approves not of them and their Prayers. So Chap. 11. <hi>I know that thou heareſt me always;</hi> and a thouſand times in the Scriptures. The drift of Chriſt in the place is (without queſtion) to ſhew the difference between ſuch as were his Sheep, and ſuch as were not his Sheep. His Sheep heard his Vioce, and they which were not his Sheep heard not his Voice. But they which were not his Sheep, nor heard his Voice, as there he ſpeaks, heard him preach outwardly as well as the reſt which were his Sheep: Beſides, they which were his Sheep, and would not hear Strangers in the Lord's Senſe, heard outwardly thoſe Strangers preach, and by hearing them diſcovered them to be Strangers, that is, falſe Prophets. The Strangers of whom he ſpeaks were of the true Church, and of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but brought falſe Doctrine tending to kill the Soul. Such Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers none ſhould hear, that is, believe and follow.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:179944:16"/>
               <p> Object. 12. <hi>The Scriptures both of the Old and New Teſtament warn God's People of falſe Prophets, which the Miniſters of that Church are, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an unlawful Calling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. They warn, <hi>not to hearken unto them, nor to believe them,</hi> Deut. 13.3. 1 John 4.1. but to try them, which without hearing them, cannot be done. Not that all falſe Prophets are to be heard by all, that they may try them, for that were to tempt God: But I now anſwer the Scripture cited, which ſpeaks of Prophets in the true Church, which were to be heard till they were orderly repreſſed, or at leaſt plainly diſcovered by their Doctrine heard to be ſuch.</p>
               <p n="2">2. No Man's unlawful outward Calling makes him a falſe Prophet, nor his outward lawful Calling a true; but his true or falſe Doctrine only makes him a true or falſe Prophet. A Man may have a lawful Office of Miniſtry, and yet be a falſe Prophet, if he teach falſe Doctrine; ſo may he be a true Prophet, if he teach the Truth, tho in an unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Antichriſtian State of Miniſtry. Yea <hi>Balaam</hi> was both a <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> in <hi>curſing</hi> (in purpoſe) where God would have him <hi>bleſs,</hi> and <hi>in teaching</hi> Balack <hi>to put a Stumbleng-block before the People of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.25. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 13.22. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15, 26. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14. and yet a true Prophet in <hi>bleſſing Iſrael</hi> by the Spirit of Prophecy, and Word of the Lord put into his Mouth. <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.5, 9, 10, &amp;c. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.23, &amp;c. He is a Prophet that ſpeaks or declares a thing paſt, preſent, or to come: And to propheſy in our Senſe, is nothing elſe but to <hi>ſpeak to Edification, Exhortation, and Comfort.</hi> 1 Cor. 14.3. He that doth this is a true Prophet, he that ſpeaks the contrary, a falſe. It were good if they, in whoſe Mouths the challenge of falſe Prophets is rifeſt, would better weigh how themſelves expound and apply the Scriptures in their propheſying, leſt notwithſtanding any outward lawful Church-ſtate, they be deeper wounded by the rebound of their Accuſations this way, then their Adverſaries.</p>
               <p>Object. 13. <hi>The Lord forbids</hi> Judah <hi>going to</hi> Gilgal <hi>or to</hi> Bethel. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.15, 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The meaning is plain, and the words expreſs that they were not to go thither to <hi>offend, and play the harlot in joyning to Idols,</hi> verſ. 15, 16, 17. This I grant is to be done in no place; but deny any ſuch thing to be done in the Hearing by me pleaded for. The Scriptures every where forbid the going, or coming to ſuch Places, or Perſons, as in or by which ſome Evil is done, to wit, for the doing of any thing evil, or unlawful in, or with them.</p>
               <p>Object. 14. <hi>They that eat of the Sacrifice partake of the Altar,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.18. <hi>ſo they that receive the Word from an unlawful Officer, partake with his Office.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:179944:17"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I deny the Conſequence; The Office is not to the Word, as the Altar is to the Sacrifice. The Altar makes the things to be offer'd, actually to become a Sacrifice, which it was not before, ſave only in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination; as Chriſt plainly teacheth, ſaying, <hi>The Altar ſanctifieth the Gift,</hi> Mat. 23.19. but ſo doth not the Office make that to become the Word of God, which was not ſo actually before. This Argument hath its ſpecial weight, being applied to Sacraments, or proper Inſtitutions. The Church and Miniſtry under God, make (in a good ſence) the Bread and Wine Sacramental, in their uſe, which before they were not. And to the Sacraments (eſpecially the Supper of the Lord) the Apoſtle in the place cited hath an eye; ſhewing the proportion between the eating of the Sacrifices in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which in that uſe became their Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and the eating the Sacrifice of the Heathens, which were their Sacraments; and the eating of the Lord's Supper, as the Sacrament of Chriſtians. With theſe things join in the laſt place, that Sacrifices con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as proper Inſtitutions, might not be <hi>offered</hi> or <hi>eaten,</hi> but in the <hi>place choſen,</hi> (Deut. 12.5, 6, 7.) and ſanctified by the Lord for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. No more may Sacraments now be eaten, but in the Church; whereas the Word may be preached to any, as well out of the Church as in it.</p>
               <p>Object. 15. <hi>The Places called Temples and Churches, having been built for Idolatry, ſhould be demoliſhed, and therefore are not to be frequented, ſpecially being accounted and made Holy Places,</hi> Deut. 12.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The difference of Places under the Law, when all other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (for the moſt ſolemn Worſhip) as oppoſed to that one place as holy, were unholy, is now taken away; ſo as no place now is holy, or unholy, as then.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Suppoſe it be the Magiſtrates Duty to deſtroy them, (of which I now diſpute not, nor how far he ſhould proceed therein) yet I deny the Conſequence, and that I may not uſe that lawfully which he ought to deſtroy.</p>
               <p>The Magiſtrate ought to have <hi>deſtroyed</hi> ſuch <hi>Cities in Iſrael,</hi> as whoſe Inhabitants had been corrupted with Idolatry, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.12, 13, 14. Yet might the Cities (if ſpared by the Magiſtrates) lawfully be dwelt in afterwards; and Synagogues in them both be built and frequented for God's moral Worſhip. <hi>Jericho</hi> ſhould have been an <hi>execration</hi> and <hi>heap for ever,</hi> 2 King. 2.3, 5. yet being built again and ſtanding, was the Seat of the School of the Prophets. The Murtherer ought to be put to death: yet if he be ſpared, and ſurvive, his Wife, Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, lawfully may, and in Conſcience ought to converſe with him according to the natural and civil relations between them and him.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:179944:17"/> 3. I know no Law in force, nor Doctrine received in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that aſcribes any holineſs to the places. And for Errors and Abuſes perſonal, they reſt in the perſons ſo erring. I ſuppoſe ſome ſuch Holineſs be abſcribed unto them, as to Holy Churches, Holy Buildings, Conſecrated Places, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet I ſee no ſufficient reaſon why I may not uſe lawfully a natural and civil place in them, for any law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Work, Civil or Religious, Private or Publick, for there is one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all theſe. If any think thoſe places like the Idolathites, he miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh therein: The things offered to Idols, and eaten in the Idols Temple, and Feaſt, were in proportion, as the Bread and Wine (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bleſſed) in the Lord's Supper; as both the Apoſtle, and reaſon of the thing manifeſts. Whereas the place which I uſe (though for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Action to be performed in it) whether in the Temple, or in mine own Houſe, hath only the Conſideration of a natural and civil Circumſtance. The Temple as a Temple (which yet I do not think is done in <hi>England</hi> by any, either received Doctrine, or Law) may be made an Idol by Conſecration; and yet every particular place in it not made unlawful for all Uſes.</p>
               <p>If any further Object, that in preaching and hearing God's Word therein, we have a religious uſe of it, they err, not conſidering that tho the Work done be religious, yet the Place is no more religious therefore than the time in which I do it. Time and Place are natural Circumſtances, and without which no finite Action can be performed; and ſome time and place more commodious and fit than others for the doing of things of all kinds. I have no more religious Uſe of the place which I hear publickly, than in which I pray privately in my Houſe or Chamber.</p>
               <p>Object. 16. <hi>Seeing whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin, what Word of God, and ſo of Faith is there for this Practice?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Every Scripture that either commands the <hi>hearing</hi> of God's Word, and promiſeth a <hi>Bleſſing to them that hear and keep it:</hi> Mat. 7.24. Luke 11.28. or that commands me to <hi>edify and build to my ſelf:</hi> 1 Pet. 2.5. or to <hi>obey the Magiſtrate;</hi> Tit. 3.1. or to <hi>follow after Peace:</hi> Heb. 12.14. or to <hi>prevent Offences:</hi> 1 Cor. 10.32. warrants and in Caſes enjoyns this Practice, ſuppoſing no Sin to be in the way: of which in anſwering the former Objections (to which I ſuppoſe all other of weight or colour may be referred) I hope I have cleared it.</p>
               <p>And for any unſatisfied, or other-wiſe minded, I wiſh I knew their Reaſons either for their good, by a ſufficent Anſwer to be given unto them, or for mine own, by admitting of them, as there may appear weight in them. In the mean while, let me intreat of the differently
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179944:18"/>minded one way or other, that they would exerciſe mutually that true Chriſtian Charity one toward another, and Compaſſion one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Infirmities, which becomes all that will be in Truth and Deed, Followers of Chriſt Jeſus; and which is moſt needful (ſpecially in things of this kind, for the preſerving of the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peaee; which Bond of Peace whilſt Men are not careful to keep inviolated by brotherly Forbearance in matters of this nature, they miſerably diſſipate, and ſcatter themſelves, and one another, even as the Ears in a Sheaf are ſcattered when the Bond breaketh.</p>
               <p>But as few or no good things of any kind are ſo well uſed by ſome, but others as much abuſe them; ſo it is to be feared, there will not want, who will change the lawful Liberty this way, into lawleſs Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs, and ſo take up inſtead of all other religious Exerciſes, a Hearing Courſe only.</p>
               <p>And thoſe ſpecially of them who diſliking the preſent Church-ſtate in <hi>England,</hi> yet want due Zeal and Love to that which themſelves ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove. Let me a little turn my Speech to ſuch, for the preventing in ſome, and remedying in others of that inordinate and broken Courſe.</p>
               <p>And firſt I demand of ſuch, what is this Courſe of hearing ſuch Miniſters, as whoſe ſtate of Miniſtry they approve not? Is it any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Ordinance left by Chriſt, and enjoyned all Chriſtians in all Ages and Places? Verily no. It were to be wiſhed that no Church-Miniſtry were to be found, which is not approveable by the Word of God, notwithſtanding any good Act performed by them that poſſeſs it. This Hearing is only a work-of natural Liberty it ſelf, as I have ſhewed, and ſanctified to Believers by their Faith. It is lawful to uſe it upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as it is to borrow of other Men; but to make it our Courſe, is to live by borrowing, which no honeſt Man, that can do otherwiſe poſſibly, would do. Yea what differs it from a kind of ſpiritual Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bondry in him that can mend it, tho with ſome Difficulty, to live in no certain Church-ſtate, and under no Church-order, and Government.</p>
               <p>To print deep in our Hearts the Conſcience of our Duties this way, let us briefly conſider how many Bonds of Neceſſity the Lord hath laid upon us, to walk in the Fellowſhip, and under the Ordinances of the miniſterial and inſtituted Church.</p>
               <p>Firſt, We have lying upon us the neceſſity of Obedience to Chriſt our Lord, in the Commiſſion Apoſtolical enjoyning, that after we be <hi>made Diſciples,</hi> as the Word is, and <hi>baptized,</hi> we be withal <hi>taught to obſerve whatſoever he hath commanded,</hi> Mat. 28.19, 20. It muſt not then ſuffice us that we are Diſciples and Chriſtians, but we muſt join here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the entire obſervation of all the Ordinances of Chriſt (as we can
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:179944:18"/>find means) from the greateſt to the leaſt. And let us beware that like the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> we call none of God's Commandments <hi>little,</hi> becauſe we would make our ſelves, and others believe, that little and light account is to be made of obſerving them; leſt we our ſelves be <hi>called little,</hi> that is, be indeed none <hi>in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Our Sins of Ignorance and humane frailty, alas, are too many, let us not add thereunto preſumptuous Sins, either of Commiſſion or Omiſſion, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God withal.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Church, and miniſtrations therein, are not needleſs, but moſt needful means ſanctified of God, and given of Chriſt for our <hi>Salvation</hi> and <hi>edification</hi> thereunto; which he that deſpiſeth, that is, doth not ſubmit his Soul and Body unto (as he hath means) and converſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in with good Conſcience, tho in Affliction and Perſecution, deſpiſeth not Man, but God and Chriſt, to the depriving of himſelf of the Fruit of God's moſt gracious preſence in his <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Temple,</hi> where he hath promiſed <hi>to dwell;</hi> and of Chriſt's <hi>aſcenſion</hi> into Heaven, for the pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of all Kingly <hi>Gifts</hi> and Largeſſes <hi>upon Men for the Work of the Miniſtry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Our great Inſirmities, whereof both the Scriptures every where, and our own experience warn us, ſhew in what great need we ſtand of all the Lord's Holy Ordinances and Inſtitutions, for the ſupplying of what is wanting in us, and correcting what is amiſs, and continuing and encreaſing of what is good, unto the coming of the Lord: where we muſt alſo take knowledg, and remember, that it is one note of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and the ſame very clear, between the wiſdom of the Fleſh, and the wiſdom of the Spirit, that the former will be ſure to provide for the Body, and outward Man, what may be, tho with danger and prejudice of the Spiritual; the other will take care and order for the Spiritual State, tho the outward pinch for it. And if any, out of the view, and perſuaſion of his own ſtrength of Grace, come to conceive, that he ſtands in no ſuch need of Chriſt's Ordinances, or of any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Fellowſhip for the diſpenſing of them: let ſuch a Man conſider, that the leſs need he hath of others by reaſon of his greater plenty of Grace received, the more need others have of him for their ſupply. But whatſoever any imagine of himſelf, the Apoſtle, who was not partial, teacheth, that the very Head (the chief and higheſt Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) <hi>cannot ſay to the Feet</hi> (the loweſt and meaneſt Members) <hi>I have no need of you,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.21.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And laſtly, It is neceſſary for our ſound and entire comfort with the Lord our God, that our Obedience be entire in reſpect of all his Holy Commandments, which we do, or can diſcern to be ſuch, and to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179944:19"/>concern us, according to that of the Man of God, <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed, when I have reſpect to all thy Commandments,</hi> Pſal. 119.6. That ſo we may have our part in the Teſtimony given by the Holy Ghoſt of <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> which was, that <hi>they were Righteous before God, walking in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> Luke 1.5, 6. That is, both in the Moral Precepts, and Sacred Ceremonies, and Inſtitutions of the Lord. Whoſe Examples we in our Place and Times are to follow, not balking with the Lord in any thing, great or ſmall: nor ſeeking ſtarting-holes, whereby to eſcape from him in his Word, which is <hi>holy, good,</hi> and <hi>pure.</hi> Good, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from our good God, good in it ſelf; and good for us, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe therein as we ought, in good Conſcience towards God, Zeal for his Ordinances, Modeſty in our Selves, and Charity towards other Men; ſpecially towards them with whom God hath joined us in the moſt and beſt things: taking heed leſt by any uncharitable, either judgment of, or withdrawing from their Perſons, for ſuch humane Frailties, as unto which, into one kind or other, all <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſinful Poſterity are ſubject; we ſin not more by our courſe held againſt them, than they by theirs in them, which God forbid.</p>
               <p>To conclude; For my ſelf, thus I believe with my Heart before God, and profeſs with my Tongue, and have before the World, that I have one and the ſame Faith, Hope, Spirit, Baptiſm, and Lord, which I had in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and none other: that I eſteem ſo many in that Church, of what ſtate or order ſoever, as are truly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that Faith (as I account many thouſands to be) for my Chriſtian Brethren; and my ſelf a Fellow member with them of that one Myſtical Body of Chriſt ſcattered far and wide throughout the World: that I have always in Spirit and Affection, all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Fellowſhip, and communion with them, and am moſt ready in all outward Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Exerciſes of Religion, lawful and lawfully done, to expreſs the ſame: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, that I am perſwaded the heating of the Word of God there preached, in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and upon the grounds formerly mentioned, both lawful and, upon occaſion, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for me, and all true Chriſtians, withdrawing from that Hierarchical Order of Church-Government and Miniſtry, and the appearances thereof: and uniting in the Order and Ordinances inſtituted by Chriſt, the only King, and Lord of his Church, and by all his Diſciples to be obſerved. And laſtly, That I cannot communicate with, or ſubmit unto the ſaid Church-Order and Ordinances there eſtabliſhed, either in State or Act, without being condemned of mine own Heart, and therein pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oking God, who is greater than my Heart, to condemn me much more. And for my Failings (which may eaſily be too many) one way or other, of Ignorance herein; and ſo for all my other Sins, I moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly crave pardon firſt, and moſt at the Hands of God. And ſo of all Men whom therein I offend, or have offended any manner of way; even as they deſire, and look that God ſhould pardon their Offences.</p>
               <p>Thus far Mr. <hi>Robinſon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="addenda">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:179944:19"/>
            <head>ADDENDA.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Judgment of ſeveral other Independent Miniſters, as well Ancient as Modern, concerning this Matter.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Henry Jacob</hi> (a ſtrict <hi>Independent</hi>) in his printed Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 1612, annexed to his Book, called, <hi>The Divine Beginning and Inſtitution of Chriſt's True Viſible Church,</hi> he hath this Aſſertion, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. For my part I never was nor am ſeparated from all publick Communion with the Congregations of <hi>England.</hi> I acknowledg there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that in <hi>England</hi> are true viſible Churches and Miniſters, tho acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally, yet ſuch as I refuſe not to communicate with; and thoſe of the Separation, in ſome Matters, are ſtreighter than I wiſh they were.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> in their <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> printed 1616, they declare, That a Miniſter receiving Prelatical Ordination, if he be a Pariſh Miniſter, it makes not a nullity of the Miniſtry of him in every reſpect beſides. That is, it makes not void all truneſs of Miniſtry in him, as a believing Congregation aſſenteth to hear him, and uſeth him for their Miniſter, when <hi>on ſome weighty occaſion, they joyn only to that which is true in the ſaid Miniſter, and teſtify in the beſt manner they can that they do ſo, orrdinarily leaving the Pariſh Congregation and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry for their Error.</hi> With all profeſſing, publiſhing, and practiſing, freely and conſtantly, the ſimple Truth therein with our ſelves; this quitteth us from all Evil, and appearance of Evil in this Matter, it being no Evil, nor appearance of Evil, to join with the Pariſh-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation and Miniſtry in ſuch reſpects; and ſo far forth as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, we ought ſometimes, on <hi>weighty Occaſions,</hi> ſo to join, and we ſin if we do not.—And though we do not think every form of Prayer ſinful and abſolutely unlawful, yet we think it not ſo profitable, and to ſome hurtful.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:179944:20"/>
            <p> Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> upon thoſe words of our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; <hi>The Scribes and Phariſees ſit in</hi> Moſes <hi>Chair, all things that they ſay unto you, that obſerve and do.</hi> Which, ſaith he, not only permits, but requires and implieth <hi>full Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The five diſſenting Brethren, (<hi>viz.</hi> Dr <hi>Goodwin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bridg.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ny,</hi> Mr. <hi>Greenhill,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sydr. Simpſon</hi>) in their Apologetical Narrative, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. they ſay, <q>We have always profeſſed, and that in thoſe times when the Churches of <hi>England</hi> were the moſt, either actually, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with Defilements, or in the greateſt danger thereof,—that we both did, and would hold a Communion with them, as the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> argues about this Matter, <hi>pag.</hi> 29. Suppoſe there ſhould be ſome humane Mixtures, are all the Ordinances of God polluted? Why do you not communicate with them in thoſe Ordinances which are pure? And in his <hi>Separation Examined,</hi> pag. 40. ſays, Corrupt Members there were enough in the Jewiſh Church, and ſo in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church ſoon after, and in the Apoſtles Times; but you have no Example of ſeparating from them.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin</hi> on the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> pag. 487, 488, 489.—His Judgment concerning Pariſh Churches, Miniſtry and Communion.</p>
            <p>In my laſt Diſcourſe I handled what was meant by the word <hi>Church.</hi> There was a neceſſity that lay upon me to open that diſtinction of Church Univerſal and Particular. I gave you two Cautions about two Errors concerning each of theſe, both toward the Church Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, and toward Particular Churches. Concerning which I muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily ſay ſomething to take away ſome Miſtakes and Miſapprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of my meaning, for I walk by this Rule, to give no offence to <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> or to the Churches of God, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>The firſt Error, I told you, was of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> of old, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Church Catholock, and reſtrained it to one part of the World; and yet the imputation of this Error lieth upon thoſe whom you call <hi>Browniſts</hi> to this day; this I cleared them from, and it is as great a clearning as can be.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Error, was of thoſe who hold Particular Churches (thoſe you call Pariſh-Churches) to be no true Churches of Chriſt, and their Miniſters to be no true Miniſters, and upon that ground for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear all Church-Communion with them in Hearing, or in any other Ordinance. And as I acquitted theſe from that other Error, ſo I
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179944:20"/>acquitted my ſelf from this, and my Brethren in the Miniſtry. I would not now have touched upon it again, but, as I ſaid, to clear, not my ſelf ſo much, as ſome miſtakes about it.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this, It was underſtood as if I ſaid, that all Pariſh-Churches and Miniſters generally, were Churches and Miniſters of Chriſt, ſuch as with whom Communion might be held. I ſaid not ſo, I was wary in my Expreſſions; I will only ſay this unto you about it, There is no Man that deſireth Reformation in this Kingdom, (as the generality of all Godly People do) but will acknowledg and ſay, that multitude of Pariſhes, where Ignorance and Prophaneſs overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the generality, Scandalouſneſs and Simony, the Miniſters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; that theſe are not Churches and Miniſters fit to be held Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with. Only this, The Ordinances that have been adminiſtred by them, ſo far we muſt acknowledg them, that they are not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called or repeated again.</p>
            <p>But here lieth the Queſtion, my Brethren, and my Meaning. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as now in ſome of the Pariſhes in this Kingdom, there are many God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men that do conſtantly give themſelves up to the Worſhip of God in publick, and meet together in one Place to that end, in a conſtant way, under a Godly Miniſter, whom they themſelves have choſen to cleave to, (tho they did not chuſe him at firſt). Theſe, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their mixture and want of Diſcipline, I never thought for my part, but that they were true Churches of Chriſt, and Siſter Churches, and ſo ought to be acknowledged. And the contrary was the Error that I ſpake againſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For holding Communion with them. I ſay, as Siſter-Churches, occaſionally as Strangers, Men might hold Communion with them. And it is acknowledged by all Divines, that there is not that Obligation lying upon a Stranger, that is not a Member of a Siſter-Church, to find fault in that Church, or in a Member of it, as doth on the Church it ſelf to which one belongeth.</p>
            <p>I will give you my Reaſons, that moved me to ſpeak ſo much. It was not ſimply to vent my own Judgment, or ſimply to clear my ſelf from that Error; but the Reaſons, or rather the Motives and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations that ſtirred me in it, were theſe;</p>
            <p>Firſt, If we ſhould not acknowledg theſe Churches, thus ſtated, to be true Churches of Chriſt, and their Miniſters true Miniſters, and their Order ſuch, and hold Communion with them too in the ſenſe ſpoken of, we muſt acknowledg no Church in all the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; none of all the Churches in <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor in <hi>Holland,</hi> nor in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> for they are all as full of mixture as ours. And to deny that to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179944:21"/>our own Churches, which we do not to the Churches abroad, nothing can be more abſurd. And it will be very hard to think, that there hath been no Church ſince the Reformation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I know nothing tendeth more to the peaceable Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt us, than to break down this <hi>Partition Wall;</hi> for there is nothing provokes more than this doth, to deny ſuch Churches to be true Churches of Chriſt. For do but think with your ſelves, and I will give you a familiar Example: You come to a Man, whom you think to be a Godly Man; you tell him, he hath theſe and theſe Sins in him, and they are great ones; it is as much as he can bear, though you tell him he is a Saint, and acknowledg him ſo. But if you come to him, and ſay, beſides this, You are a Limb of the Devil, and you have no Grace in you; this provokes all in a Man, when there is any ground in himſelf to think ſo, or in another to judg him ſo. So it is here, Come to Churches, and ſay, You have theſe Defects among you, and theſe Things to be reformed; but if you will come, and ſay, Your Churches and your Miniſters are Antichriſtian, and come from <hi>Babylon,</hi> there is nothing provokes more. Therefore, if there be a Truth in it, (as I believe there is) Men ſhould be zealous to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it; for this is the great <hi>Partition Wall</hi> that hindreth of twain making one.</p>
            <p>Then again, This is that which I conſider, and it is a great Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration alſo. I know that Jeſus Chriſt hath given his People Light in matters of this nature by degrees. Thouſands of good Souls that have been bred up and born in our Aſſemblies, and enjoy the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God, and have done it comfortably, cannot ſuddenly take in other Principles, you muſt wait upon Chriſt to do it.</p>
            <p>In this Caſe, Men are not to be wrought off by Falſhoods, God hath no need of them. No, rather till Men do take in Light, you ſhould give them all that is comfortable in the condition they are in; we ſhould acknowledg every good Thing in every Man, in every Church, in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Thing, and that is a way to work upon Men, and to prevail with them; as it is <hi>Philem.</hi> verſ. 6. <hi>That the Communication of thy Faith may become effectual by the acknowledgment of every good thing, which is in you in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> It is that which buildeth men up, by acknowledgment of every good thing that is in them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The laſt Inconvenience is this, It doth deprive men of all thoſe Gifts that are found amongſt our Miniſters, and in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that they cannot hold any Communion or Fellowſhip with them. So that I profeſs my ſelf as zealous in this Point, as in any other I know; And for my part this I ſay, and I ſay it with much integrity,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179944:21"/>I never yet took up Religion by Parties, in the lump; I have found by trial of things, that there is ſome Truth on all ſides. I have found Holineſs where you would little think it, and ſo likewiſe Truth; and I have learned this Principle, which I hope I ſhall never lay down till I am ſwallowed up of Immortality; and that is that which I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, To acknowledg every good Thing, and hold Communion with it, in Men, in Churches, or whatſoever elſe. I learn this from <hi>Paul,</hi> I learn this from Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, he <hi>filleth all in all;</hi> he is in the Hearts of his People, and filleth them in his Ordinances to this day; and where Jeſus Chriſt filleth, why ſhould we deny an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a right hand of Fellowſhip and Communion.</p>
            <p>My Brethren, this Rule that I have now mentioned, (which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I have lived by, and ſhall do while I live) I know I ſhall never pleaſe Men in it. Why? it is plain, For this is the nature and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Mankind; if a Man diſſents from others in one thing, he loſeth them in all the reſt; and therefore if a Man do take what is good of all ſides, he is apt to loſe them all, but he pleaſeth Chriſt by it, and ſo will I for this particular.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> pag. 177. of <hi>Evangelical Love,</hi> ſaith, That it is pleaded indeed, the Subſtance of the Worſhip of God ought to be no other than what Jeſus Chriſt hath appointed; yet the Manner and Mode of performance of what he doth command, with other Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, for Order and Decency, may lawfully be inſtituted by the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Church; let it therefore at preſent be granted (ſays he) that ſo they may be by them, who are perſwaded of the lawfulneſs of thoſe Modes, and of the things wherein they conſiſt.</p>
            <p>Indeed he very much condemns Communion with ſuch Apoſtatical Churches who are guilty of Idolatry, and require unſcriptural Terms of Communion: but what Churches thoſe are, remains to be proved. I am ſure he aſſerts, that many Errors in Doctrine, Diſorders in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Adminiſtrations, irregular walking in Converſation, with neglect and abuſe of Diſcipline in Rulers, may fall out in ſome Churches, and yet not evacuate their Church-State, or give ſufficient warrant for any Perſon to leave their Communion, and to ſeparate from them, <hi>Pag.</hi> 76. <hi>Evang. Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, pag. 176. We wholly deny that the Miſtakes of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in joining themſelves unto ſuch Churches as have no warrantable Inſtitution, ought to be any cauſe of the diminiſhing of our Love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them; for they may be Perſons born of God, united to Chriſt, partakers of the Spirit, and belong to the Church Catholick Myſtical,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179944:22"/>which is the firſt principal Object of all Chriſtian Love and Charity; notwithſtanding their Errors and Wandrings from the Truth in this Matter.</p>
            <p>And the ſaid Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> who in his <hi>Diſcourſe of the Work of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in Prayer,</hi> writes againſt the making or compoſing of Forms of Prayer for our ſelves to be uſed privately, deſires the Reader, <hi>p.</hi> 200. to obſerve that he <hi>doth not argue againſt Forms of Prayer as unlawful to be uſed.</hi> And, <hi>pag.</hi> 222. he grants, that <hi>Men or Churches may agree upon a preſcribed Form by common conſent, as judging and avowing it beſt for their own Edification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> pag. 228. Whether they are approved or diſapproved of God, whether they are lawful or unlawful, we do not conſider, but only whether they are for Spiritual Benefit and Advantage for the good of our own Souls, and the Edification of others, as ſet up in competition with the Gift before deſcribed. <hi>So that it ſeems the Doctor doth not judg ſuch Forms of Prayer unlawful which are for the good of our own Souls, and the Edification of others, and which are not in competition with the Gift before deſcribed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore (<hi>p.</hi> 231, <hi>&amp;</hi> 232.) ſuppoſing that thoſe who make uſe of, and plead for Forms of Prayer, eſpecially in Publick, do in a due manner prepare themſelves for it by holy meditation, with an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bring their Souls into a holy frame of Fear, delight and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God; let it alſo be ſuppoſed that they have a good End and Deſign in the Worſhip they addreſs themſelves unto, namely, the Glory of God, and their own Spiritual Advantage; the Prayers themſelves, tho they ſhould be in ſome things irregular, may give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to exerciſe thoſe Acts of Grace which they were otherwiſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for: And I ſay yet further, that whilſt theſe Forms of Prayer are cloathed with the general Notions of Prayer, that is, are eſteemed as ſuch in the minds of them that uſe them, are accompanied in their uſe with the Motives and Ends of Prayer, expreſs no Matter unlawful to be inſiſted on in Prayer, directing the Souls of Men to none but lawful Objects of Divine Worſhip and Prayer, the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit; and whilſt Men make uſe of them with the true deſign of Prayer, looking after due aſſiſtance unto Prayer, I do not judg there is any ſuch Evil in them, as that God will not communicate his Spirit to any in the uſe of them, ſo as that they ſhould have no holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him in and under them. Much leſs will I ſay, that God never therein regards their Perſons, or rejects their praying as unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: For the Perſons and Duties of Men may be accepted with God, when they walk and act in ſincerity according to their Light, tho in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:179944:22"/>many things, and thoſe of no ſmall importance, ſundry Irregularities are found, both in what they do, and in the manner of doing it. Where Perſons walk before God in their Integrity, and practiſe nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Light and Conviction in his Worſhip, God is merciful unto them, altho they order not every thing according to the Rule and Meaſure of the Word. So was it with them who came to the Paſſover in the days of <hi>Hezekiah, They had not cleanſed themſelves, but did eat the Paſſover otherwiſe than it was written,</hi> 2 Chron. 30.18.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>p.</hi> 235. he grants, That ſuch Forms of Prayer <hi>have not any intrinſecal Evil in the compoſition of them;</hi> but argues againſt the <hi>ſetting up</hi> and preſcribing ſuch <hi>Forms of Prayer</hi> univerſally, <hi>in oppoſition, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the excluſion of free Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And, p.</hi> 236. If they appear not contrary unto, or inconſiſtent with, or are not uſed in a way excluſive of that Work of the Holy Spirit in Prayer, which we have deſcribed from the Scripture, nor are reducible to any Divine Prohibition, I ſhall not contend with any about them.</p>
            <p>Much more might have been collected, even out of the Writings of the Congregational Miniſters concerning theſe weighty Matters, but this is ſufficient. I know the Reader will be ſollicitous to know their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and kneeling thereat; but I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, at preſent, I cannot find they ſay any thing particularly about it, only the practice of ſome of them in receiving the Sacrament ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manner of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> does evince, that all of them do not deny the lawfulneſs of it, but that they may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times communicate there, tho ordinarily they do with their own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches, for better-Edification, as they judg.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Tombs,</hi> a learned Miniſter, and a great <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> wrote a Book to prove it lawful, both to Hear and <hi>Communicate</hi> with the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and his practice at <hi>Salisbury</hi> was conformable thereunto.</p>
            <p>Indeed the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> that are called <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> both Ancient and Modern, do generally allow the lawfulneſs of Communicating with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> tho at the ſame Time they held the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies to be burthen ſome, and therefore would avoid them if they could; but if they could not have the Sacrament otherwiſe, they took it as they could have it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus ſays Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>in his</hi> Chriſtian Directory, <hi>pag.</hi> 859. <hi>Firſt Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> Had I my choice, I would receive the Lord's Supper ſitting; but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179944:23"/>where I have not, I will uſe the Geſture which the Church uſeth. And it is to be noted, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> requireth the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants only to <hi>receive it kneeling,</hi> but not to eat and <hi>drink it kneeling,</hi> when they have received it.</p>
            <p>And his Reſolution of this Caſe ought to be conſidered, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>May the Communion-Tables be turned Altar-wiſe? and railed in? And is it lawful to come up to the Rails to Communicate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1.—God hath given us no particular Command or Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition about theſe Circumſtances, but the general Rules for Unity, Edification, Order and Decency: Whether the Table ſhould ſtand this way or that way, here or there, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he hath not particularly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They that turn the Table Altar-wiſe, and rail it in, out of a deſign to draw Men to Popery, or in a ſcandalous way which will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Men to, or in Popery, do ſin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. So do they that rail in the Table, to ſignify that the Vulgar or Lay-Chriſtians muſt not come to it, but be kept at a diſtance; when Chriſt in his Perſonal Preſence admitted his Diſciples to communicate at the Table with himſelf.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But where there are no ſuch Ends, but only to imitate the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents that did thus, and to ſhew reverence to the Table on the account of the Sacrament, by keeping away Dogs, keeping Boys from ſitting on it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The profeſſed Doctrine of the Church condemneth Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, the real Corporal Preſence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as ours doth. In this Caſe Chriſtians ſhould take theſe for ſuch as they are, indifferent things, and not cenſure or condemn each other for them; nor ſhould any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them on any that think them unlawful.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And to Communicate, is not only lawful in this Caſe, where we cannot prove that the Miniſter ſinneth, but even when we ſuſpect an evil Deſign in him, which we cannot prove; yea, or when we can prove that his perſonal Interpretation of the Place, Name, Situation, and Rails, is unſound; for we aſſemble there to communicate in, and according to the profeſſed Doctrine of Chriſtianity, and the Churches and our own open Profeſſion, and not after every private Opinion and Error of the Miniſter. As I may receive from an <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> or <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſt,</hi> notwithſtanding his Perſonal Errors; ſo may I from another Mans, whoſe Error deſtroyeth not his Miniſtry, nor the Ordinance, as long as I conſent not to it; yea, and with the Church profeſs my diſſent.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Yet <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> every free Man that hath his choice, ſhould chuſe to Communicate, rather where there is moſt Purity and leaſt Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, than with thoſe that ſwerve more from regular Exactneſs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:179944:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
